<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A most choice historical compendium fitted for the use of all ingenious and inquisitive persons who are curious to know what wonderfull events have come to pass for almost 1000 years, under the figure 8, from 818 to 1688 inclusive : wherein is briefly comprised, the life and death, rise and fall of kings, queens, noblemen, clergymen, warriors and several famous poets : with many other curious remarks and observations, not here mention'd / written in a plain method, by A.M., Gent.</title>
            <author>A. M., Gent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51537</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9727</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12330237</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12330237</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59632</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51537)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59632)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 640:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A most choice historical compendium fitted for the use of all ingenious and inquisitive persons who are curious to know what wonderfull events have come to pass for almost 1000 years, under the figure 8, from 818 to 1688 inclusive : wherein is briefly comprised, the life and death, rise and fall of kings, queens, noblemen, clergymen, warriors and several famous poets : with many other curious remarks and observations, not here mention'd / written in a plain method, by A.M., Gent.</title>
                  <author>A. M., Gent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 153, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Weld ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [2]-[5] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59632:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A MOST CHOICE <hi>Hiſtorical Compendium,</hi> Fitted for the uſe of all Ingenious and Inquiſitive Perſons: WHO Are curious to know what wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Events have come to paſs for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt 1000 Years, under the Figure 8, from 818. to 1688. Incluſive.</p>
            <p>Wherein is briefly Compriſed, The Life and Death, Riſe and Fall of Kings, Queens, Noblemen, Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gymen, Warriors, and ſeveral famous Poets. With many other Curious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks and Obſervations, not here mention'd.</p>
            <p>Written in a Plain method, by <hi>A. M.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Weld,</hi> at the Crown near <hi>Temple-Bar</hi> in <hi>Fleet ſtreet,</hi> 1692.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59632:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:59632:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE beſt and muſt infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Guide we have upon Earth <hi>(The Holy Writ)</hi> informs us, that the wife and Omnipotent Creator of the World, was pleaſed to ſet out ſix days to finiſh that vaſt piece of work, and bleſſed the Seventh day, and hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it; Yet afterward, when the wickedneſs of Mankind increaſed to that heighth, as to provoke the ſame Creator to deſtroy his works again by
<pb facs="tcp:59632:3"/> a Flood. He commanded <hi>Noah</hi> to build an Ark, for the preſervation of all manner of Beaſts, Fowle, and Fiſh, <hi>&amp;c. Noah</hi> had alſo a precept to enter the Houſe of Safety, and to take along with him his Family, which in all amounted but to eight perſons. Out of which number, the whole earth was repopulated, and repleniſhed to the incredulous number of Millions of Perſons already known and found out to this day, and finding many memorable paſſages, happening under that number in many places abroad, eſpecially in our own Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and that alſo in very late years, the laſt being 1688. I ſhall here preſent to thy unbyaſſed Judgment many Heroick actions done by our own Countrymen, both at Home and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad: The Riſe and Fall, the Birth and Death; the conferring of Honour and Preferment, and alſo the Degrading of many perſons, both Divines, Lawyers, Warriers and Seamen; Lords, Knights,
<pb facs="tcp:59632:3"/> Gentlemen, and Private men, ſome of a low degree, and ſome famous Poets, born and bred in the Engliſh Climate, and all theſe begun or ended under the figure of <hi>eight,</hi> and no other. As for example, <hi>England</hi> was firſt ſo called by <hi>Egbert</hi> a Saxon King in 818. <hi>Ethelbert</hi> another Saxon King began his Reign 858. And ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more Engliſh Kings and Queens: ſo likewiſe Sir <hi>Hugh Calveley,</hi> Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh</hi> and many other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, very remarkable in their Lives and Fortunes, continuing on the ſame to this wonder-working year 1688. as thou mayſt ſee in this Treatiſe fully explain'd. Here is alſo preſented to thy veiw the Spaniſh Armadoe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of what Ships and other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations in 1588. the Murder of King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt. The Death of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurping <hi>Oliver.</hi> The death of Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey.</hi> The Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Plot. The publiſhing of a Birth of the Prince of <hi>Wales.</hi> The land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:59632:4"/> of the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> The departure of King <hi>James</hi> and his Q. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> out of the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and alſo an account of other matters included in the aforeſaid years, very profitable both for preſent and future Generations, and in theſe later years being matter of fact, and truly ſtated and demonſtrated, may be a good Copy to write after; learning there by to carry our ſelves ſteadily and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in our ſeveral ſtations, both in times of War and Peace, Proſperity and Adverſity. Now if any one ſhould ask thee, why I took no other figure to end in, tell him it would have ſwelled the Book to a greater Price, intending this only portable for the Pocket, and for ſuch as are not willing to go to a higher rate: and if that anſwer is not ſufficient, let them take the other eight remaining figures, and uſe to their beſt advantage and pleaſure; if this Tract finds good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, it may be an encouragement for a ſecond adventure after the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:59632:4"/> way and method for the future. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever at preſent I will no longer detain thee in the Porch, but open a paſſage into a fair Field, full of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety and pleaſure, deſiring thee to reap the ſame, by peruſal of theſe my pains and willing endeavours.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:59632:5"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59632:5"/>
            <head>A CHOICE And moſt uſeful COMPENDIUM.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>ENgland</hi> was firſt ſo called by <hi>Egbert</hi> a <hi>Saxon</hi> King, who began his Reign in 818.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ethelbert</hi> another <hi>Saxon</hi> King began his Reign in 858.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alfred</hi> another <hi>Saxon</hi> King firſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided <hi>England</hi> into Shires, in the year 888.</p>
            <p>Organs were brought into ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral uſe in Churches, about the year 828, and much improved by <hi>Bernard</hi> a <hi>Venetian,</hi> and an incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parble Muſician.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:59632:6"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Herbert de Boſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was a <hi>Manubus</hi> unto <hi>Tho. Becket,</hi> at whoſe Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyring he was preſent, and had the diſcretion to make no reſiſtance; he wrote the ſtory of his Maſter's death. Going over into <hi>Italy</hi> he was by Pope <hi>Alex.</hi> 3. made Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Beneventum,</hi> and in <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1178. created Cardinal.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Agelnoth</hi> the Good, Archbiſh. of <hi>Cant.</hi> is ſaid to have given at <hi>Rome</hi> 100 Talents of Silver, and one of Gold, for the Arm of St. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> B: of <hi>Hippo.</hi> He expended much in repairing his Cathedral lately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by the <hi>Danes,</hi> aſſiſted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in by the bounty of King <hi>Canutus.</hi> He dyed 1038.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Walt Epiſc. Carliel</hi> no great Clerk, being made Lord Treaſurer of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> he avowed his Accounts even when juſtly charged with a 100 <hi>l.</hi> Debt to the Exchequer; upon which he reſigned his Biſhoprick and became a Fryer at <hi>Oxford,</hi> where he dyed 1248. Where note that ſome
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59632:6"/> perſons will deſcend from a higher to lower degree, to obtain pardon for ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edward</hi> Son to <hi>Edgar</hi> K. of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> was in his Infancy whipt by <hi>Elfrida</hi> his Mother-in-Law with wax Candles, ſo that afterward he could never indure the ſight of any ſuch Candles; when he was King, <hi>Elfrida</hi> managed for the moſt part all the Affairs of State, and afterwards cauſed this <hi>Edward</hi> to be ſtab'd at <hi>Corſe</hi> Caſtle, whither he had come to viſit her; <hi>An.</hi> 978. intending by that murther to make way for her Son <hi>Ethelred</hi> to the Kingdom. He was buried at <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> which was formerly called St. <hi>Edwards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Matthew Gournay,</hi> Born at <hi>Stoke</hi> under <hi>Hambden, Somer.</hi> where his family hath flouriſhed ſince the Conqueſt, and there built both a Caſtle and a College. He was the honour of his Houſe in the Reign of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3<hi>d.</hi> He fought at the Siege of <hi>Algiers</hi> and <hi>Benemazin</hi> againſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59632:7"/> the <hi>Saracens,</hi> at <hi>Ingen, Poictiers, Sluee, Creſſy,</hi> againſt the <hi>French,</hi> and at <hi>Nazaran</hi> under the <hi>Black Prince</hi> in <hi>Spain.</hi> His Armour was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held by martial men with much civil veneration, with whom his faithful Buckler was a relique of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem. He dyed in peace, aged 90. odd years, <hi>an.</hi> 1378.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Steph. Langton,</hi> born in <hi>England,</hi> bred in <hi>Paris,</hi> was one of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Scholars of the Chriſtian world in his age. He was conſecrated Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal of St. <hi>Chryſogone,</hi> then by the Pope intruded Archbiſhop of <hi>Cant.</hi> in defiance of King <hi>John;</hi> he wrote co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ments on all the old, and ſome of the new Teſtament. He firſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided the Bible into Chapters, which <hi>Robert Stephens</hi> a Frenchman ſubdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into Verſes. <hi>Langton</hi> divided alſo the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing King <hi>John</hi> to ſad extremities. He dyed, and was buried at <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury, an.</hi> 1220.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:59632:7"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Stephen de Fulborn</hi> was made Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Waterford,</hi> and Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and after Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Tuam</hi> and (twice) Lord Chief Juſtice of that Kingdom. He dyed <hi>an.</hi> 1288. and was buried in Trinity Church in <hi>Dublin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Dunſtan,</hi> born in, and Abbot of, <hi>Glaſſenbury,</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> and <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and for promoting of Monkery was reputed a Saint. His skill in Smithery was ſo great, that the Goldſmiths in <hi>London</hi> are incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated by the name of the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of St. <hi>Dunſtans.</hi> He dyed <hi>Anno</hi> 988. He was the ſtricteſt of the Clergy, againſt the marriages of Prieſts in his life time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sewald,</hi> bred in <hi>Oxford,</hi> was Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar to St. <hi>Edward,</hi> who was wont to ſay to him, <hi>Sewald, Sewald,</hi> thou wilt have <hi>many afflictions and dye a Martyr:</hi> Nor did he miſs much of his mark therein, though he met with peace and plenty at firſt when Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59632:8"/> but afterwards oppoſing the Pope, who intruded one <hi>Jordan</hi> an <hi>Italian</hi> to be Dean of <hi>York,</hi> he was for his contempt Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Note that at the ſame time there were 300: benefices poſſeſſed by <hi>Italians,</hi> who did not only teach in the Church, but <hi>miſteach by their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcivious and debauched converſations.</hi> Let us now return to <hi>Sewald,</hi> who never returned into the Popes favour, but dyed of grief in the ſtate of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, <hi>An.</hi> 1258. yet was he reputed a Saint in <hi>vulgar eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eleanor,</hi> Eldeſt Daughter to King <hi>Ed.</hi> I. and Queen <hi>Eleanor</hi> born at <hi>Windſor,</hi> afterwards was married by Proxy (a naked ſword interpoſing between her and his body) to <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſ.</hi> King of <hi>Arragon,</hi> who dyed before the conſummation of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage. The Princeſs was afterwards married to <hi>H.</hi> 3. Earl of <hi>Berry</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> from whom the Dukes of <hi>Anjou</hi> and Kings of <hi>Sicil</hi> are deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, She dyed <hi>An.</hi> 1298.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:59632:8"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Edward</hi> III. Son to <hi>Ed.</hi> II. and Queen <hi>Iſabel</hi> born at <hi>Windſor,</hi> a pious and fortunate Prince, was Paſſive in depoſing of his Father, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on in his minority by his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and <hi>Mortimer.</hi> His <hi>French</hi> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories ſpeak both of his Wiſdom and Valour: and though the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts by <hi>H.</hi> 5. were <hi>thicker,</hi> his were broader (in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land)</hi> though both in length a like, as loſt by by their immediate Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors. He was the firſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> King that coyned Gold. He firſt ſtamped the <hi>Rorſe Nobles,</hi> having on one ſide <hi>Jeſus autem tranſiens per medium illorum ibat,</hi> and on the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe his own Image, with a Sword and Sheild ſitting in a Ship waving on the Sea. He had a numerous and happy Iſſue by <hi>Philippa</hi> his Queen, after whoſe death being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt 70 years old he caſt his aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions on <hi>Alice Pierce</hi> his Paramour to his diſhonour, it being true what <hi>Epictetus</hi> returned to <hi>Adrian</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59632:9"/> asking of him what love was. <hi>In puero, pudor; in virgine, Rubor; in Foemina furorin Juvene, Ardor; in ſene Riſus.</hi> In a Boy Baſhfulneſs, in a Maid Bluſhing, in a Woman Fury, in a young Man Fire, in an Old Man Folly. However this King had few equals, none ſuperiours for Wiſdom, Clemency and Courage. He dyed <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1378.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wulſtan</hi> of <hi>Brandsford,</hi> was Prior of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and built a moſt beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Hall in his Convent. Hence he was preferred Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> 1338. He was <hi>verus pontiſex</hi> in the Grammatical notation thereof, building a fair Bridge at <hi>Brandsford</hi> over the River <hi>Teme,</hi> and dyed not long after.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jo. Everſden</hi> was breda Monk in <hi>Bury</hi> Abby, whereof he was Cellerer or Caterer: but mounting himſelf above this mean imploy; he buried himſelf in <hi>Poetry, Law,</hi> and <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> whereof he wrote a fair Volume from the beginning of the World.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59632:9"/> Being a Monk he was not fond of Fryers: And obſerveth that when the <hi>Franciſcans</hi> firſt entred <hi>Bury,</hi> a few years before his death, there hapened a hideous <hi>Hurricane,</hi> lev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Trees, Towers; yet went they out with a clam, at the time of the diſſolution. He dyed 1338.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1378. Note that in this year (in the Reign of <hi>Richard</hi> II.) the <hi>Suſſexians</hi> of <hi>Rye</hi> and <hi>Winchel-ſea,</hi> imbarked for <hi>Normandy,</hi> and afterwards entred by night into a Towncalled <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>Port,</hi> took all ſuch Priſoners who were able to pay ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, and ſafely returned home with their ſpoils; amongſt which were ſome Bells the <hi>French</hi> had formerly taken from the Towns in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which they lately invaded. It was a worthy advice which <hi>William</hi> Earl of <hi>Arundel</hi> gave to his Son <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Fitz-Allen, never to truſt his Neighbours the French,</hi> which I would commend to the inhabitants of this
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59632:10"/> County, and indeed now and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever to all <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Stratford,</hi> of <hi>Stratford, War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wickſhire,</hi> being born there, was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred by the Pope to the Biſhopr. of <hi>Wincheſt.</hi> whereupon falling into the diſpleaſure of <hi>Richard</hi> II. for a time, he took it in ſo ill part, that he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook that King whilſt in his extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity: this coſt him the diſpleaſure of the Queen Mother and <hi>Edw.</hi> III. till at laſt converted by his conſtancy, they turned their frowns into ſmiles upon him. When he was Archbiſhop of <hi>Cant.</hi> he furniſhed the King with great ſums of money at his firſt ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth for <hi>France:</hi> But when the King ſent to him again for another ſupply, inſtead of Coyn, the Biſhop ſent him Counſel, whereat the King returning into <hi>England,</hi> was ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offended, that the Biſhop was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to paſs his publick purgation in <hi>Parlia.</hi> by which he was reſtored to the reputation of his Innocence. He
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59632:10"/> built and bountifully endowed a Beautiful Colledge in <hi>Stratford.</hi> He dyed <hi>Anno</hi> 1348. having been a man of great charity, meekneſs and moderation. <hi>Ralph Straford</hi> his Kinſman was Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> and there being a grievous Peſtilence there, this Biſhop bought a piece of Land for the burial of the Dead, lying near <hi>Smithfield</hi> called <hi>No mans Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euſtathius de Fauconbridge,</hi> was choſen Biſhop of <hi>London An.</hi> 6. <hi>Hen.</hi> III. He was choſen Chief Juſtice, then Chancellor of the Exchequer, and afterwards Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> and twice Ambaſſador to the King of <hi>France:</hi> He dyed <hi>October</hi> 31. 1228. and was buried in the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maurice Chamnee,</hi> bred a Fryer in the <hi>Charter-Houſe.</hi> He only eſcaped when 18 of his Order loſt their lives, (by him written) for refuſing the Oath of ſupremacy. 'Tis ſaid he warped to the will of <hi>H.</hi> 8. to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his Covent from deſtruction.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59632:11"/> He dyed beyond the Seas about 1580.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Amias Preſton,</hi> of an ancient Family at <hi>Cricket</hi> in <hi>Somerſet.</hi> An. 88. ſeized on the Admiral of the <hi>Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſes,</hi> wherein the Governour with moſt of his men were burnt or killed. He took the Town of <hi>Puerto Sancto,</hi> and the Iſle of <hi>Cochi;</hi> ſurprized the Fort and Town of <hi>Coro,</hi> ſacked the City of St. <hi>Jago,</hi> put to Ranſom the Town of <hi>Cumana,</hi> and entred <hi>Jamaica</hi> (all in the <hi>Weſt Indies)</hi> and returned home ſafely. He ſent a challenge to Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh</hi> the Privy Counſellor, which was by him refuſed, having a Wife and Children and a fair Eſtate, and Sir <hi>Amias</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a private and ſingle Perſon, though of good quality; becauſe Sir <hi>Walter</hi> condemned thoſe for ill humours, <hi>where the Hangman gives the Garland.</hi> Theſe two Knights were reconciled afterwards, and Sir <hi>Amias</hi> dyed about the beginning of King <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:59632:11"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Rob. de Leic,</hi> a Frank in <hi>Oxford;</hi> was one that brought Preaching in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to faſhion in that Age: He wrote of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Roman Chronological</hi> Computation. He died at <hi>Lichfield,</hi> 1348.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>John Philpot,</hi> (whoſe Family hath long reſided in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pton-Court</hi> in <hi>Kent,)</hi> was bred a Grocer in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> whereof he was Mayor 1378. He ſet forth a Fleet in the Reign of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 2. at his own coſt, to repreſs the Inſolence of one <hi>John Mercer,</hi> a <hi>Scot,</hi> who was taken with all his Ships, and rich Plunder therein. Two Years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he conveyed an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Britain,</hi> in Ships of his own hiring, and with his own Money releaſed more than 1000 Arms there, which the Soldiers had formerly engaged for their Victuals. The Nobility ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed him for acting without a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; yea, <hi>pro tantorum ſumptuum pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mio veniam vix obtinuit.</hi> That is, He ſearcely obtained his Pardon by a great charge, and by r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ward and gifts.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:59632:12"/>
            <p> Sir <hi>Hugh Calvely,</hi> born at <hi>Calvely</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> of whom 'tis ſaid, He could feed as much as two, and fight as much as ten men: his ſtrong Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite would digeſt any thing but an injury; ſo that killing a Man is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported the cauſe of quitting his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and going for <hi>France;</hi> where he became ſuch an excellent Soldier, that he converted the moſt difficult Atchievements into eaſie performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, by martial Valour. He was one of 30 <hi>Engliſh</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> who in a Duel encountered as many <hi>Britains.</hi> He revenged the Blood of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, who whilſt his hands were tied behind him, were ſlain before his Face, <hi>An. ult. E.</hi> 3. 'Twas he that after an unfortunate Voyage of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nobility, <hi>An.</hi> 1. <hi>R.</hi> 2. took <hi>Barkbulloign,</hi> and 25 other <hi>French.</hi> Ships, beſides the Caſtle of <hi>Mark</hi> lately loſt, and by him recovered; and the next Year he ſpoiled <hi>Eſtaples,</hi> with the Plunder of which he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched the <hi>Calicians.</hi> He married the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59632:12"/> Queen of <hi>Arragon,</hi> whoſe Arms are quartered on his Tomb. He died 1388.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Booth,</hi> Bachelor of Law, was conſecrated Biſhop of <hi>Exeter, An.</hi> 6. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4. He built the Biſhops Chair, or Seat, in its Cathedral, which hath not his equal in <hi>England;</hi> but the ſofeſt Cuſhion belonging to it was taken away, when Biſhop <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcy</hi> alienated the Lands thereof. When the Biſhop had finiſhed this Chair, he could not quietly ſit down there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, ſuch were the troubles ariſing from the Wars between <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſt.</hi> therefore retiring to his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Habitation at <hi>Horſley</hi> in <hi>Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> He died 1478. and was buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in St. <hi>Clement Danes</hi> in <hi>London.</hi> There was an elder Brother, Sir <hi>Rog. Booth,</hi> of <hi>Barton</hi> in <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Margaret,</hi> Wife of <hi>Ralph Nevil</hi> third Earl of <hi>Weſtmoreland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theorithoid,</hi> a holy Nun at <hi>Barkin</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> after her death was repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Saint. She died 678. This Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nery
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59632:13"/> was valued 1000 <hi>l.</hi> yearly rent, at the diſſolution in <hi>Henry</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sim</hi> of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> born in <hi>London,</hi> was preferred Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> by <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. He gave the firſt leave to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens thereof to fortifie that place with a Ditch and Walls, 1298. And no leſs was his care of the Church, than of the City, making good Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes; whereby it was ordered even unto our Age.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry,</hi> eldeſt Son to King <hi>John,</hi> born at <hi>Wincheſter An.</hi> 1208. was a pious, but poor King: He was at firſt poſtponed to King <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>France;</hi> afterwards imbroiled with the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons Wars, and impriſoned; yet at laſt he obtained a comfortable old Age, by the means of his Son Prince <hi>Edward.</hi> He would be governed by thoſe he knew wiſer than himſelf: the main cauſe of his peaceable death, and pompous burial in the <hi>Abbey</hi> of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> of his own foundation.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:59632:13"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Philip de Repton</hi> became D. D. in <hi>Oxford,</hi> a great Aſſerter of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Wickliff,</hi> but he recanted and became a <hi>Perſecutor;</hi> wherefore he was termed (by thoſe he mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted) <hi>Rampington.</hi> He was made Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> Chancellor of <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln, An.</hi> 1408. and was created by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> 12. <hi>Card.</hi> of St. <hi>Nerius, &amp;c.</hi> though he had ſolemnly ſworn he would make no more Cardinals 'till the Schiſm in <hi>Rome</hi> were ended. He reſigned his Biſhoprick, after 12 Years poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Will. White,</hi> a Wicklevite, and the firſt married Prieſt ſince the Pope's ſolemn prohibition thereof; was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant to his calling, and was as a <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge daily on the Wing,</hi> removing from place to place: he was ſeized, condemned, and burnt at <hi>Norwich</hi> 1428. As for Marian Martyrs, thoſe in this Shire ſuffered, either by the cruelty of <hi>Griffin</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> or <hi>Thornton</hi> Suffragan of <hi>Dover.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:59632:14"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>William Gray,</hi> Son to the Ld. <hi>Gray</hi> of <hi>Codnor,</hi> was as honourable. He firſt ſtudied in <hi>Baliol Coll.</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> then at <hi>Ferrara</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> where he was an Auditor of <hi>Guarinus</hi> of <hi>Vero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</hi> He was made by <hi>H.</hi> 6. Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator in the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and was freely elected to the Biſhoprick of <hi>Ely</hi> by <hi>Edw.</hi> 4. He was <hi>Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer,</hi> the laſt <hi>Clergy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Man</hi> that ever was preferred to that Office, until Biſhop <hi>Juxton</hi> in our days enjoyed it. He died 1478. and lies buried in the Church of <hi>Ely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Will. Caxton</hi> of <hi>Caxton,</hi> a diligent and learned Man, bred beyond the Sea, and lived 30 Years in the Court of <hi>Mary</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> Siſter to K. <hi>Edw.</hi> 4. He continued Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chronicon unto the end of that King with good Judgment and Fidelity: He collected and printed all <hi>Chaucers</hi> Works, and on many accounts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved well of Poſterity, and died 1488.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:59632:14"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Stephen Brown,</hi> Grocer, was born at <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> afterwards Knighted, and made Lord Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> 1438. In which Year happened a great Famine, cauſed much by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonableneſs of Weather, (but more by ſome huckſtering Husbandmen, who may be properly called <hi>Knaves</hi> in Grain.) Sir <hi>Stephen</hi> ſent ſome Ships to <hi>Dantzick,</hi> whoſe ſeaſonable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn with <hi>Rye,</hi> ſuddenly ſunk Grain to reaſonable rates, whereby many a languiſhing Life was preſerved. He was one of the firſt Merchants, who in want of Corn ſhewed the <hi>Londo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> the way to the <hi>Barn-Door.</hi> I mean into <hi>Spruceland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edw. Fox,</hi> born in <hi>Dureſly</hi> in <hi>Glou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſterſhire,</hi> was Almoner to King <hi>H.</hi> 8. he firſt brought Dr. <hi>Cranmer</hi> to the knowledge of the King: He was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards Biſhop of <hi>Hereford,</hi> and was the principal <hi>Pillar</hi> of the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as to the managerie of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick part thereof: Of the many Books he wrote, that <hi>De differentia</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:59632:15"/> 
               <hi>utriuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> poteſtatis</hi> was his maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece. He was imployed on ſeveral Embaſſies into <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> and died <hi>Anno</hi> 1538.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mary Groy,</hi> the youngeſt Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> frigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the infelicity of her two el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Siſters forgot her honour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member her <hi>ſafety,</hi> and married one whom ſhe could <hi>love,</hi> and none need fear, <hi>Martin Kayes</hi> of <hi>Kent,</hi> Eſq; <hi>Serjeant-Porter,</hi> and died without Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, 20. <hi>Ap.</hi> 1578.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>James Goldwel,</hi> born at great <hi>Chart</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> was Dean of <hi>Salisbury, Secr.</hi> to <hi>Edw.</hi> 4. and at laſt Biſhop of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich:</hi> He repaired the Church of great <hi>Chart,</hi> and founded a Chapel on the South-ſide thereof: he died 1598.</p>
            <p>His Brother <hi>Thomas,</hi> by Qu. <hi>Mary,</hi> was preferred Biſhop of St. <hi>Davids;</hi> and in the Reign of Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> he went to <hi>Rome,</hi> where he procured Indulgences to ſuch as ſhould go in Pilgrimage to St. <hi>Winifreds</hi> Well in his Dioceſs.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:59632:15"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Robert Braſſy,</hi> born at <hi>Bunbury, (i. e. Boniface-bury)</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire;</hi> bred D. D. in <hi>King's Colledge</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> whereof he was Provoſt: being lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſtout, he publickly prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted againſt the Viſitors in Q. <hi>Mary's</hi> Reign, as to his own College, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by taking off the edg of theſe perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Commiſſioners. When ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Doctors of <hi>Cambridge</hi> were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to ſell their Right in <hi>Sturbridg-Fair</hi> for a trifle to the <hi>Townſ-men,</hi> he daſhed their deſigns; which manly oppoſition prevented the Vice-Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor's holding the Stirrup to the <hi>Mayor.</hi> He died <hi>Ann. Dom.</hi> 1558. and lies buried on the South-ſide of the Chapel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Stuckley</hi> was a younger Brother; of an ancient and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Family, near <hi>Illfracomb,</hi> in <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>von,</hi> one of good parts, and great ambition, having ſpent his Patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and undertaking the Plantation of <hi>Florida,</hi> he bluſhed not to tell Queen <hi>Elizabeth, That he preferred</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:59632:16"/> 
               <hi>rather to be Soveraign of a Mole-hill, than the higheſt Subject to the greateſt King in</hi> Chriſtendom; <hi>and that he was aſſured he ſhould be a Prince before his Death. I hope</hi> (ſaid the Queen) <hi>I ſhall hear from you when you are ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in your Principality. I will write unto you</hi> (quoth <hi>Stuckley.) In what Language?</hi> (ſaid the Queen.) He returned, <hi>In the Stile of Princes, To our dear Siſter.</hi> His fair project be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing blaſted for lack of Money, he went into <hi>Ireland,</hi> where miſſing the preferment he expected, he went o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with treacherous intent into <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:</hi> There he wrought himſelf with ineredible dexterity into the very bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> 5. vaunting that with 3000 <hi>Soldiers</hi> he could beat all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> out of <hi>Ireland.</hi> The Pope loading him with the Titles of Baron of <hi>Roſs,</hi> Viſc. <hi>Murrough,</hi> Earl of <hi>Wex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> Marq. of <hi>Lemſter,</hi> furniſhed him with 800 Soldiers, paid by the King of <hi>Spain</hi> for the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But <hi>Stuckley</hi> choſe rather to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59632:16"/> accompany <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> with 2 <hi>Mooriſh</hi> Kings into <hi>Africa:</hi> where behaving himſelf valiantly with his 800 Men, in the Battel of <hi>Alcaſer,</hi> he was ſlain, <hi>An.</hi> 1578. In vain he had given good counſel to theſe furious Kings to refreſh their faint Soldiers before the Fight; for ruſhing on after their firſt Landing, they buried themſelves together in the ſame ruin.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>A fatal Fight, wherein one day was ſlain</l>
               <l>Three Kings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that were, and one that would be fain.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>Agnes Preſt</hi> lived at <hi>Northcot</hi> in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> and was indicted before <hi>W. Stanford</hi> Judge of the Aſſize <hi>an.</hi> 2. 3. <hi>P.</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> her own Husband and Children being her greateſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors, from whom ſhe fled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they would force her to Maſs: but being preſented to the Biſhop of <hi>Exeter,</hi> ſhe was condemned for
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59632:17"/> denying the Sacr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment of the <hi>Altar,</hi> after which ſhe refuſed money from all well affected people, ſaying, <hi>ſhe was going to that City where money had no maſtery;</hi> ſhe was burnt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Walls of <hi>Exeter</hi> in <hi>Sothonhay,</hi> Nov. 558. ag. 54.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tho. Leaver, B. D.</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> fled in the <hi>Marian</hi> days, and became Paſtor of the Engliſh Exiles at <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> in <hi>Switz.</hi> He wrote a book en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled <hi>The right Path way to Chriſt:</hi> He dyed after his return into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> 1558.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hen. Stafford,</hi> Baron of <hi>Stafford,</hi> was Son to <hi>Ed.</hi> Duke of <hi>Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> beheaded under <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. the Barony deſcended unforfeited to this <hi>Henry,</hi> placed here not as a <hi>trans</hi> but a <hi>cis reformation</hi> man, for tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlating the book of Dr. <hi>Fox Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Hereford,</hi> (favourer of <hi>Luther)</hi> into Engliſh, <hi>of the differences of power Eccleſiaſtical and Secular:</hi> He dyed 1558. ſome months before the beginning of Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:59632:17"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Peter Petow,</hi> of an ancient Family, flouriſhing for a long time at <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterton,</hi> was a <hi>Franciſcan,</hi> afterwards Cardinal, being created by Pope <hi>Paul</hi> III. who alſo made him <hi>Legat a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere,</hi> and Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury.</hi> Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> in favour to Cardinal <hi>Poole,</hi> prohibited this Legat's entrance into her Court. He died in <hi>France</hi> 1558.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Savage,</hi> born at <hi>Mackleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire;</hi> his Father (a Knight) bred in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> a Doctor of Law. Hence he was preferred Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> and at laſt Arch-biſhop of <hi>York.</hi> A greater Courtier than Clerk, dextrous in managing ſecular Affairs, a mighty Huntſ-man. He was the firſt who was privately <hi>inſtalled</hi> by his Vicar: He maintained a nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Family, and built much at <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>roby,</hi> and <hi>Cawood,</hi> in <hi>Yorkſ.</hi> He died 1508. his Body being buried at <hi>York,</hi> his <hi>Heart</hi> at <hi>Macklesfield,</hi> in a Chapel of his own Erection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Godfrey Gouldsbrough,</hi> born in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> bred in <hi>Trinity-College,</hi> and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59632:18"/> afterwards Fellow thereof: at laſt was conſecrated Biſhop of <hi>Glouce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> 1598. one of the ſecond ſett of Proteſtant Biſhops, after thoſe in the <hi>Marian</hi> days; and before thoſe who come within our Memory. He gave 100 Marks to <hi>Trinity</hi> College, and died ſome Months after.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Will. Drury,</hi> deſcended of a worſhipful Family, long flouriſhing, at <hi>Hantſtead</hi> in <hi>Suffolk;</hi> anſwered his name <hi>(Drury</hi> in Sax. Pearle,) in the preciouſneſs of his diſpoſition, <hi>clear</hi> and <hi>hard, valiant</hi> and <hi>innocent.</hi> His Youth he ſpent in the <hi>French</hi> Wars, his middle in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and his old Age in <hi>Ireland:</hi> He was Knight-Marſhal of <hi>Berwick;</hi> at which time the <hi>French</hi> had poſſeſſed themſelves of the Caſtle of <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> in the minority of King <hi>James.</hi> Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> imployed this Sir <hi>William,</hi> with 1500 Men to beſiege the Caſtle. Which ſervice he worthily perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, in reducing it in few days to the right owner thereof. He was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59632:18"/> Lord Preſident of <hi>Munſter;</hi> where he executed impartial Juſtice, in ſpite of the Owners thereof. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring <hi>Kerry</hi> with a competent train of 140 Men, with which he forced his return through 700 Men, belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Earl of <hi>Deſmond,</hi> who claimed <hi>Kerry</hi> as a Palatinate pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly to himſelf. In the laſt Year of his Life he was made Lord-Deputy of <hi>Ireland,</hi> dying at <hi>Waterford,</hi> 1598.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tho. Cavendiſh,</hi> Eſq; of <hi>Trimley, Suffolk,</hi> intending Foreign Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, on his own coſt victualled and furniſhed three Ships, (the leaſt of Fleets,) <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Deſire,</hi> Admiral, 120 Tuns; the <hi>Content,</hi> Vice-Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, 40, and the <hi>Hugh-Gallant,</hi> Reer-Admiral, 40 Tuns; all three man'd with 123 Men; and ſetting to Sea from <hi>Plimouth, July</hi> 21. 1586. en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred the mouth of the <hi>Magellan-Straits,</hi> 7 <hi>January</hi> following, where they ſuffered much hunger. Mr. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vendiſh</hi> named a Town there <hi>Port-Famine:</hi> The <hi>Spaniards</hi> intending to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59632:19"/> fortifie the Straits, and engroſs the paſſage, were ſmitten with ſuch a Mortality, that ſcarce 5 of 500 did ſurvive. On <hi>Feb.</hi> 28. they entred the South-Sea, and frequently land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as they ſaw occaſion. Many were their conflicts with the Natives, more with the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> coming off gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in moſt, and ſavers in all Encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that in <hi>Quinterno</hi> excepted, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pril</hi> 1. 1587. where they loſt 12 men of account, the cauſe that they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ſunk the Reer-Admiral for want of men to manage her. Of the many Prizes he took, the St. <hi>Anne</hi> was the moſt conſiderable, being the Spaniſh Admiral of the South-Sea, of 700 Tun, and 190 Men; there were 122000 <hi>Pezos</hi> (each worth 8 Shill.) of Gold, with other rich La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, as Silks and Musk. Mr. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vendiſh</hi> landed the Spaniards, and left them plentiful Proviſions, ſurround<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> and returning for <hi>England,</hi> landed at <hi>Plimouth, Sept.</hi> 9. 1588. In his next Voyage he was
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59632:19"/> ſevered from his Company near <hi>Port Deſire,</hi> by him ſo called formerly in the <hi>Magellan-ſtraits,</hi> and never ſeen or heard of afterwards.</p>
            <p>Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> eldeſt Daughter to K. <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. and Q. <hi>Katherine</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> was born at <hi>Greenwich, Feb.</hi> 18. 1518. She derived a great Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit from her Father, and her Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from her Mother. She attained to the Crown by complying with the Gentry of <hi>Norfolk</hi> and <hi>Suffolk,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing them to continue Religion, as Eſtabliſhed by King <hi>Edw.</hi> VI. After the breach of which Promiſe, ſhe never proſpered; loſing ſucceſſively the hearts of her Subjects, the hopes of a Child, the company (not to ſay affection) of her Husband, the City of <hi>Calais,</hi> her Mirth, her Health, and her Life, which ended <hi>November</hi> 17. 1558. Cardinal <hi>Poole</hi> died the ſame day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> That in this Queens ſhort Reign, being but 5 Years &amp; 4 Months, many were made Martyrs for the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59632:20"/> Truth of the Goſpel; the Romiſh Superſtition ſo much prevailing and tyrannizing, that 408, or more, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered Fire and Faggot; whereof 44 of note were in the County of <hi>Eſſex.</hi> This was carried on chiefly by Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Bonner,</hi> who was a Baſtard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of one <hi>Savage</hi> a Prieſt, (brother to Sir <hi>John Savage,</hi> Knight of the Garter, Privy-Counſellor to <hi>H.</hi> VII.) His Mother Concubine to this Prieſt, was ſent out of <hi>Cheſhire</hi> to cover her <hi>ſhame,</hi> and laid down her burden at <hi>Elmley</hi> in <hi>Worceſterſhire,</hi> where this bouncing Babe <hi>Bonner</hi> was born; he cauſed the death of twice as many Martyrs as all the Biſhops in <hi>England</hi> beſides; after 10 Years Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the <hi>Marſhalſea</hi> he died, and was buried in St. <hi>George</hi>'s Church-Yard in <hi>Southwark.</hi> But enough of this <hi>Heroſtratus,</hi> who burned ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny living Temples of the Holy Ghoſt. Let them which would be more fully informed of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> read <hi>Fox</hi>'s Works lately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59632:20"/> in Folio, with new Copper Cutts.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1558. The ſecond Daughter to K. <hi>H.</hi> 8. born at <hi>Greenwich,</hi> who coming to the Crown at Q. <hi>Mary</hi>'s death upon the 17th <hi>Novemb.</hi> (ſtill a vulgar error, accounted for Queen <hi>Eliz. birth day)</hi> who was born in <hi>Septemb.</hi> She was Heir to the <hi>Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Bounty, Courage,</hi> and <hi>Succeſs</hi> of her <hi>Father,</hi> beſides <hi>Goodneſs</hi> wherein ſhe was daughter to her Mother. Her learning appears in her two Latine Speeches to the Univerſity, and a third a l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ttle better than <hi>extempore</hi> to the <hi>Poland</hi> Embaſſador. Her bounty was founded on merit. Her cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage was undaunted, never making her ſelf ſo <hi>cheap</hi> to her Favourites but that ſhe valued her own authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. A prime Officer (with a white ſtaffe) was commanded by the Queen to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a place then void, on one of her ſervants whom ſhe commended un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. <hi>Pleaſeth</hi> your <hi>Highneſs, Madam</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>the diſpoſal</hi> thereof
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59632:21"/> 
               <hi>belongeth to me by vertue of this white Staff conferred on me.</hi> True, ſaid the Q. yet I never gave you your Office ſo abſolutely, but I ſtill reſerved my ſelf of the <hi>Quorum;</hi> but of the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, Madam</hi> (returned the Lord) preſuming on the favour of her Highneſs. Hereat the Q. in ſome paſſion, ſnatching the ſtaff out of his hand, you ſhall acknowledge me, ſaid ſhe, of the <hi>Quorum quarum quorum,</hi> before you have it again. The Lord waited ſtaffleſs almoſt a day before the ſame was reconferred. Her ſucceſs was admirable, keeping the K. of <hi>Spain</hi> at Arms end all her Reign, by her Policy and Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. She was much beloved by all her people, in ſo much that ſince it hath been ſaid, that Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> might do that lawfully, which K. <hi>James</hi> might not. Her popularity having ſugared ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, her Subjects thanking her for thoſe Taxes, which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to pay to her Succeſſor. You ſhall find more of her valour and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59632:21"/> Noble Actions in 1588.. She dyed at <hi>Richmond.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Winter,</hi> Knight and Vice-Admiral of <hi>England,</hi> aſſaulted the Fort of French, in the Iſland of <hi>Inchkeeih</hi> in <hi>Edenburgh Frith:</hi> He (with Sir <hi>Tho. Smith)</hi> demanded the reſtitution of <hi>Calais;</hi> he conducted a great Treaſure of the <hi>Genoa</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants ſafely into the <hi>Netherlands</hi> in deſpite of the French oppoſing him 1568. He (with <hi>Rob. Beale)</hi> was ſent into <hi>Zealand</hi> to demand reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ships. He did ſignal ſervice when the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fleet was fallen towards the coaſt of <hi>Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> 1588. <hi>Lidney</hi> Houſe in <hi>Glou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> the ſeat of the Family, had produced many more Mariners hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in Sea Voyages.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Ruſſel,</hi> born at <hi>Kingſton Ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, Dorſ.</hi> bred beyond the Sea, was a man of great accompliſhment, and was recommended by <hi>Phil.</hi> King of <hi>Caſtile</hi> (Father to <hi>Ch.</hi> 5. Emp.) to <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. as a perſon of great abilities,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59632:22"/> he could ſee more with his <hi>one eye</hi> than many others could with <hi>two.</hi> King <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. made him a Controller of the Houſhold, and Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor, and <hi>an.</hi> 1538. created Lord <hi>Ruſſel;</hi> and made him Keeper of the Privy Seal. A good ſhare of the golden ſhowr of Abby Lands fell into his lap. K. <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. (who made him Earl of <hi>Bedford)</hi> ſent him down to ſuppreſs the <hi>Weſtern</hi> commotion, and relieve <hi>Exeter:</hi> Which he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with great wiſdom, valour, and ſucceſs, and ſome few years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dyed, and was buried at <hi>Cheineys</hi> in <hi>Buckinghamſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Cecil,</hi> our <hi>Engliſh Neſtor</hi> for Wiſdom and Vivacity, born at <hi>Burn</hi> in <hi>Lincolnſ.</hi> was Secretary and Treaſurer above 30 years together. He ſteered the Court at his pleaſure, and whilſt the Earl of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> would endure no equal, and <hi>Suſſex</hi> no ſuperior, therein he by ſiding with <hi>neither</hi> ſerved himſelf with <hi>both:</hi> you may eaſily imagin how high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59632:22"/> the wiſe Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> valued ſo great a <hi>Miniſter of State,</hi> coming once to viſit him when ſick, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much hightned with her head at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, (then in faſhion) the Lord's ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, who conducted her through the Door, may your <hi>Highneſs</hi> (ſaid he) be pleaſed to ſtoop: the Queen returned, <hi>for your Maſters ſake I will ſtoop, but not for the King of Spains.</hi> All <hi>England</hi> in that Age was beholden to him for his bounty (as well as the poor in <hi>Stamford)</hi> for whom he erected a fair Bead-houſe, acknowledged under God and the Q. their Proſperity, the fruit of his prudence. He dyed very aged 1598.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jane Cecil,</hi> Wife to Sir <hi>Rich.</hi> Eſq; and Co-heir to the worſhipful fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of <hi>Ekinton</hi> and <hi>Walcot,</hi> ſaw (being near a 100 years of age) the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of her Son Sir <hi>William,</hi> Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer of <hi>England;</hi> ſhe Leaded and Paved the <hi>Friday Market-croſs at Stamford,</hi> beſides 50<hi>l.</hi> given to the Poor. She dyed 1588. and was bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59632:23"/> in St. <hi>Martins</hi> in <hi>Stamford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Barnaby Potter</hi> was born within the <hi>Barony</hi> of <hi>Kendal Weſtmerl.</hi> 1578. and bred at <hi>Queens</hi> Coll. in <hi>Oxford,</hi> whereof he became Provoſt: he was chaplain in Ordinary to Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> being accounted at Court the <hi>Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tential Preacher,</hi> and by K. <hi>Ch.</hi> the I. was preferred Biſhop of <hi>Carliſle.</hi> He was commonly called the <hi>Puritani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Biſhop, and they ſaid of him in the time of King <hi>James,</hi> that <hi>Organs</hi> would blow him out of the Church: which is not probable, becauſe he loved <hi>Vocal Muſick,</hi> and could bear his own part therein. He was a conſtant Preacher, and a hard Student: He dyed in honour, being the laſt Biſhop that dyed a Member of <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Roger Aſcham,</hi> born at <hi>Kerby-wick,</hi> and bred in St. <hi>John</hi>'s College in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> was Orator and <hi>Greek</hi> Profeſſor of the Univerſity; and in <hi>an.</hi> 1. <hi>Mary</hi> wrote Letters to 40 odd ſeveral Princes, the meaneſt whereof was a Cardinal. Traveling into
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59632:23"/> 
               <hi>Germany,</hi> he was familiar with <hi>John Sturmius,</hi> after his return he was teacher to the Lady <hi>Eliz.</hi> to whom (after ſhe was <hi>Queen)</hi> he became Secretary for her <hi>Latine</hi> Letters; he was an honeſt man, a good Archer, and much delighted with Cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fighting. His Latine ſtile was facile and fluent, witneſs his Letters. His <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is a Book good for Young Men, his <hi>Schoolmaſter</hi> for Old, and his Epiſtles for all men. He dyed in <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1568. and was buried in St. <hi>Sepulchres</hi> in <hi>Lond.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tho. Benham,</hi> Fellow of <hi>Magdalens</hi> coll. in <hi>Oxford,</hi> renounced Popery <hi>an.</hi> 1. <hi>Mariae,</hi> he aſſiſted <hi>Hen. Bull</hi> one of the College, to wreſt out of the hands of the Choriſters, the cenſer when about to offer their ſuperſtitious <hi>Incenſe;</hi> flying into <hi>Germany</hi> he lived at <hi>Baſil,</hi> Preacher to the Engliſh Exiles; towards the end of <hi>Queen Mary,</hi> he was ſecretly ſent over to be Superintendant of the <hi>London Conventicle</hi> (the only true
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59632:24"/> Church in the time of Perſecution) where with all his caution he hardly eſcaped. In <hi>an.</hi> 2. of Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> he was conſecrated Biſhop of <hi>Coven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> and <hi>Lichfield:</hi> He dyed in <hi>Febr.</hi> 1578.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Frances Sidney,</hi> Aunt to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowed Sir <hi>Philip,</hi> ſhe beſtowed on the Abby Church of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> a Salary of 20 <hi>l. per annum</hi> for a Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity Lecture, and founded <hi>Sidney Suſſ.</hi> coll. in <hi>Cambr.</hi> She was Relict of <hi>Tho. Ratcliff</hi> Earl of <hi>Suſſex:</hi> She dyed childleſs 1588.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Nich. Bacon</hi> Knight, born not far from St. <hi>Edm. Bury,</hi> of a very ancient family, and bred in <hi>Ben.</hi> college in <hi>Cambr.</hi> (in which he built a beautiful Chapel) after he had ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died the Common Law, was made Attorny to the Court of <hi>Wards,</hi> when he was preferred Lord Keeper of the Great <hi>Seal. An.</hi> 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1558. He married <hi>Ann</hi> ſecond Daughter to Sir <hi>Ant. Cook</hi> of <hi>Giddy Hall</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> Governour to K. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. Queen
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59632:24"/> 
               <hi>Elizabeth</hi> relied on him as her Oracle in Law, who that he might clear the point of her Succeſſion, derived her right from a Statute which allowed the ſame, tho' there was a Statute which made the Q. illegitimate in the days of her Father remained unrepealed, the rather becauſe Lawyers maintain, That a Crown once worn, cleareth all defects of the wearer thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Armigel Waad,</hi> born of an ancient family in <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> was Clerk of the Counſel to <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. a man of great accompliſhments, imployed in ſeveral Embaſſies, and the firſt Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhman who diſcovered <hi>America:</hi> He had by two Wifes 20 children, whereof Sir <hi>Wil. Waad</hi> was the Eldeſt, a very able Gentleman, and Clerk of the Council to Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> this <hi>Armigel</hi> dyed in <hi>June, an.</hi> 1568. and was buried at <hi>Hampſtead</hi> in <hi>Middleſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Martin Forbiſher</hi> Knight, born nigh <hi>Doncaſter Yorkſhire,</hi> was the firſt Engliſhman who firſt diſcovered the North way to <hi>China</hi> and <hi>Cathay,</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:59632:25"/> whence he brought great ſtore of black ſoft Stone, ſuppoſing it to be ſilver Ore, but it proved uſeleſs. He was valiant and violent. He was Knighted for his ſignal ſervice in <hi>an.</hi> 88. having (with 10 Ships) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended <hi>Breſt</hi> Haven in <hi>Brittain</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a far greater power of the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> he was ſhot in the ſide, his wound not being mortal in it ſelf was rendred ſuch by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skillfulneſs of his Chirurgion, who having taken out the bullet, left the Bombaſt behind, wherewith the ſore feſtred, and the worthy Knight dyed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Michael,</hi> Under-Sheriff to Sir <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony Hungerford comit. Wiltſ.</hi> 1558. in the laſt of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> was a right godly man. When the Writ, <hi>de Haereticis comburendis,</hi> for the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of <hi>R. White</hi> and <hi>Jo. Hunt,</hi> was brought to him, inſtead of burning them, he burnt the Writ, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſame could be renewed, Dr. <hi>Geffery</hi> (the bloody Chancellour of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59632:25"/> 
               <hi>Salisbury</hi> who procured it) and Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> were both dead.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edm. Gueſt,</hi> Born at <hi>Aſſerton York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> was D. D. in <hi>Kings College</hi> in <hi>Cambridge.</hi> He was Almoner to Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> by whom he was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> then of <hi>Salisbury;</hi> having written many books, he dyed 1578.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry Rowlands,</hi> bred in <hi>Oxford,</hi> was conſecrated Biſhop of <hi>Bangor</hi> 1598. he bought four new Bells for the Tower of St. <hi>Aſaph,</hi> whereof the biggeſt coſt 100 <hi>l.</hi> he alſo gave to <hi>Jeſus College</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> Means for the maintenance of two Fellows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Katharine,</hi> Daughter of Sir <hi>Tho. Par,</hi> was born at <hi>Kendal</hi> Caſtle, which deſcended to her Father from the <hi>Bruſſes</hi> and <hi>Roſſes</hi> of <hi>Werk:</hi> She was firſt married to <hi>John Nevil</hi> Lord <hi>Latimer,</hi> and afterwards to K. <hi>H.</hi> 8. She was a great favourer of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and would earneſtly argue for it. Once politick <hi>Gardiner</hi> had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt got her into his clutches, had
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59632:26"/> not Divine Providence delivered her: yet a Jeſuit (who was neither Confeſſor nor Privy Counſellour to the King) tells us, that the King in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, if longer ſurviving, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head her for an <hi>Heretick.</hi> She was afterwards married to Sir <hi>Thomas Seymour</hi> Baron of <hi>Sudley</hi> and Lord Admiral; and dyed in childbed of a Daughter 1548.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry</hi> 8. Son of <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. born at <hi>Greenwich,</hi> was a Prince in whom great Vertues &amp; no leſs Vices werein a manner equally contemperated; he was a man of an uncontroulable ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, carrying a <hi>Mandamus</hi> in his Mouth, ſufficiently ſeated, when he put his hand to his Hilt, he awed all to his obedience, which was great in a King, and neceſſary in a <hi>Father</hi> of his <hi>Country.</hi> In the Play of K. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. there was a weak whining Boy that perſonated that King; one of his fellow Actors perceiving him to act more like a Mouſe than Man, told him, if you ſpeak not <hi>Hoh</hi> with a
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59632:26"/> better <hi>Spirit;</hi> your Parliament <hi>will not grant you a penny of Money.</hi> He came to the Crown in 1508. Many were the acts and changes in his Reign. He diſſolved as many <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries</hi> and <hi>Religious Houſes,</hi> as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted yearly to 1865 12 <hi>l.</hi> beſides the two Univerſities, and divers <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries</hi> which were undervalued. And though the Pope ſtiled him <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender</hi> of the <hi>Faith</hi> (by reaſon of a Book he writ againſt <hi>Martin Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther)</hi> yet he rejected his <hi>Holineſs,</hi> and made himſelf ſupreme without him. And Sir <hi>Tho. Moor</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Fiſher</hi> loſt their Heads, becauſe they refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Oath of Supremacy; and yet this King, as appears by the ſix Articles, enacted by Parliament againſt the Proteſtants (called the <hi>Cat</hi> with <hi>ſix Tailes)</hi> viz.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That after the words of <hi>confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or conſecration</hi> the <hi>real</hi> and <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural body and blood of Chriſt</hi> as he was conceived and Crucified was in the Sacrament, and no other ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59632:27"/> conſiſting in the form of Bread and Wine, beſides the ſubſtance of Chriſt, <hi>God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and <hi>Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That Communion in both kinds, was not neceſſary unto Salvation, the Fleſh only in the form of Bread ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Prieſts after they had received Orders might not marry by the Law of God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the Vows of Chaſtity ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Man or Woman, ought by Gods Laws to be obſerved.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That private Maſſes were neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the people, and agreeable to the Law of God.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That <hi>Auricular</hi> Confeſſion was expedient to be retained and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in the Church of God.</p>
            <p>Now I hope none will deny, that what miſchief and confuſions enſued, and cauſed by him as the Papiſts deeply condemn him for to this day, and tell us (our Religion came out of his—) That he lived and dyed as ſevere a Roman Catholick as any
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59632:27"/> of them hath ſhewed themſelves in this our Age.</p>
            <p>And for his Wives he was dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous in changing, beheading one of them, and the very next day marrying another; but hear him on his death bed ſpeaking thus:</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Three</hi> Kates, <hi>two</hi> Nans, <hi>and one dear</hi> Jane <hi>I wedded,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>One Spaniſh, one Dutch, and four Engliſh Wives:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>From two I was divorced, two I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>One dyed in Childbirth, and one me ſurvived.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>They that will be more and better informed of this King's Reign, let them read his Life written by that excellent and learned Lord <hi>Herbert.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Tho. Offley</hi> of <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> bred a <hi>Merchant Taylor</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> whereof he became Lord Mayor; in his Mayoralty he began the cuſtom of <hi>Night Bellmen.</hi> He was the <hi>Zacheus</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> for his high <hi>Charity,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathing the half of his Eſtate (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59632:28"/> 5000 pound) to the poor, though he had children of his own; yea he appointed that 200 <hi>l.</hi> (left to his Son <hi>Hen.)</hi> ſhould be taken out of the other half, and imployed to charitable uſes. Mr. <hi>Hugh Offley</hi> Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-Seller, Sheriff of <hi>London An.</hi> 1588. gave 600 pound to the City to put forth young men. Mr. <hi>Rob.</hi> Brother to <hi>Hugh</hi> gave 600 pound for 24 young men in <hi>Cheſter,</hi> whereof 12 were Apprentices. On the firſt of theſe I ſuppoſe theſe Rhimes were made:</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Offley <hi>three diſhes had of dayly Roaſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>An Egg, an Apple, and the third a Toaſt.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>Feaſting himſelf moderately, that he might feed others by his bounty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Miles Coverdaile</hi> of <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came an <hi>Auguſtine</hi> Fryer, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards quitting that profeſſion, he went into <hi>Germany,</hi> he laboured greatly in tranſlating the Bible, and writing other books. He was made D. D. at <hi>Tubing,</hi> and returning into
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59632:28"/> 
               <hi>England</hi> was made Biſhop of <hi>Exeter,</hi> by K. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. <hi>An.</hi> 1. <hi>Mary</hi> he was depoſed, though ſaved from Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom, by the mediation of <hi>Fred.</hi> King of <hi>Denmark:</hi> being enlarged he went over into <hi>Germany,</hi> whence in the Reign of Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned into <hi>England,</hi> but not to <hi>Exeter.</hi> He was one of thoſe that ſolemnly conſecrated <hi>Matthew Parker Archbiſhop of Canterbury</hi> at <hi>Lambeth:</hi> He dyed 1588. and lies buried in St. <hi>Bartholomews</hi> behind the <hi>Exchange, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Chriſt. Wray</hi> Knight, was born in the Pariſh of <hi>Bedal Yorkſhire,</hi> which made his Daughter <hi>Frances</hi> Counteſs of <hi>Warwick</hi> ſcatter her benefactions thicker in that place: His Anceſtors came out of <hi>Cornwal,</hi> where his name is right ancient; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bred in the Law, he was by Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> made Lord Chief Juſtice of the <hi>Kings Bench;</hi> he was moved with no fear but that of the Judge of the world; he was <hi>pro tempore</hi> Lord pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59632:29"/> Seal, and ſat chief in the Court, when Secretary <hi>Daviſon</hi> was ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the Star Chamber, concurring with the reſt of the Commiſſioners to lay a Fine on him. His benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to <hi>Magdalen</hi> college in <hi>Cambridge</hi> was both bountiful and ſeaſonable. This worthy Judge dyed <hi>May 8th.</hi> 1588.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rob. Crowley</hi> of <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> bred in <hi>Oxford,</hi> confuted <hi>Miles Hogheard,</hi> who writ againſt the poor Proteſtants. He fled to <hi>Frankford</hi> in Queen <hi>Mary's</hi> days, and in the Reign of Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> was made Vicar of St. <hi>Giles</hi> without <hi>Cripplegate London,</hi> where he lies buried, having dyed 1588.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cock,</hi> was in 1588. <hi>a Cock of the Game,</hi> being the only man of note amongſt the Engliſh, who fighting a Volunteer in his own Ship, loſt his life, to ſave his Queen and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:59632:29"/>
            <p> Sir <hi>John Howard,</hi> of <hi>Barkſhire</hi> Kt. Son to Sir <hi>Rob. Howard,</hi> ſoon after was created a Baron by <hi>Edw.</hi> IV. and Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> by K. <hi>Rich.</hi> III. as Kinſman, and one of the Heirs of <hi>Anne,</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Norfolk,</hi> whoſe Mother was one of the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Tho. Mowbray,</hi> D. of <hi>Norfolk.</hi> Soon after he loſt his Life in <hi>Boſworth-Field,</hi> in the quarrel of him who had given him his Honour. From him deſcended the noble and numerous Family of the <hi>Howards,</hi> of whom 4 Earls, <hi>viz. Arundel, Nottingham, Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk,</hi> and <hi>Barkſhire;</hi> and 2 Barons, <hi>viz. Mowbray,</hi> and <hi>Eſcrick,</hi> ſat in the laſt Parliament of K. <hi>Charles</hi> I. <hi>Verſtegan,</hi> the great Antiquary, will have their Name to be <hi>Holdward,</hi> Keeper of a Caſtle, or Truſt; and they have well anſwered unto their Name. Did not <hi>Tho. Howard,</hi> Earl of <hi>Surrey,</hi> well <hi>hold his ward</hi> by <hi>Land,</hi> when in the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. he conquered the Scots in <hi>Flodden-Field,</hi> and took <hi>James</hi> the <hi>4th.</hi> their King, Priſoner? And did
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59632:30"/> not <hi>Charles Howard,</hi> afterwards Earl of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> hold his <hi>ward,</hi> by <hi>Sea,</hi> in 1558, when the <hi>Armado</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Howard,</hi> Son to <hi>Thomas</hi> D. of <hi>Howard,</hi> was by Queen <hi>Mary</hi> cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated Baron of <hi>Effingham,</hi> and made Lord-Admiral of <hi>England.</hi> He was one of the firſt favourers and further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the diſcovery of <hi>Ruſſia.</hi> He died 1548. whoſe Son</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles</hi> ſucceeded his Father in the Admiralty; an hearty Gentleman, and cordial to his Soveraign, of a moſt proper Perſon, one reaſon why Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> reflected ſo much upon him. The firſt evidence he gave of his proweſs, when the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors Siſter, the ſpouſe of <hi>Spain,</hi> with a Fleet of 130 Sail, paſſed the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Seas, his Lordſhip, accompanied with 10 Ships only, environed their Fleet, and enforced them to <hi>ſtoop Gallant,</hi> and ſtrike Sail. In 88. at the firſt news of the Spaniards approach, he towed at a Cable, with his own
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:59632:30"/> hands, to draw out the <hi>harbour-bound Ships</hi> into the Sen. He was Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Sea Forces at the taking of <hi>Cadiz,</hi> and for his good ſervice there, he was made Earl of <hi>Notting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</hi> He reſigned his Admiralty in the Reign of K. <hi>James,</hi> to the D. of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> and died not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>D.</hi> of <hi>Medina Sidonia,</hi> Admiral of the Spaniſh Fleet, <hi>An.</hi> 88. beholding <hi>Mount Edgcomb</hi> in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to Sir <hi>Rich. Edgcomb,</hi> who at one time, for ſome good ſpace, gave Entertainment to the <hi>Engliſh, Spaniſh,</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Admirals, and many other Nobles at <hi>Mount Edgcomb,</hi> a ſquare Structure, having a ſtately Hall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fording a delicate ſound, as one en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth it, a Parlour and Dining-Room, giving a large proſpect both of Sea and Land: It is near <hi>Plimouth;</hi> the Ground about it being ſtored with Wood, Timber, Fruit, Deer, and Conies, ſufficient Paſture, Meadow and Arable Land, Marle, Stone, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:59632:31"/> and of an high ſituation. And this <hi>Medina</hi> was ſo much in love with it, was reſolved to have it for his own poſſeſſion in the partage of this Kingdom, which ſhould have been in 88.</p>
            <p>And here I think it very neceſſary before we proceed any further, to make a ſmall deſcription of this <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Invaſion, called, <hi>The Invincible Armado;</hi> which put <hi>England</hi> into ſuch a conſternation, when it ſhould have been invaded, in the Reign of Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1588. <hi>viz.</hi> 150 Ships, ſome 1000 Tuns.</p>
            <list>
               <item>65 Galleoons.</item>
               <item>25 Terras, 500 Tuns.</item>
               <item>19 Pinnaces, ſome 100 Tuns.</item>
               <item>20 Carvills.</item>
               <item>10 Fulvas, 6 Oars a piece.</item>
               <item>4 Galeaſſes.</item>
               <item>4 Gallies.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In all, 57868 Tuns.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:59632:31"/>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2630 Pieces of Cannon.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Enſigns</cell>
                     <cell>171</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mariners</cell>
                     <cell>8650</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Soldiers</cell>
                     <cell>19295</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gally-ſlaves</cell>
                     <cell>2808</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Volunteers</cell>
                     <cell>224</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Allowed Servants for the Can.</cell>
                     <cell>167</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>For the Hoſpital</cell>
                     <cell>58</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Chyrurgeons</cell>
                     <cell>108</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Church-Men</cell>
                     <cell>108</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>All theſe Preparations of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> did not daunt, or diminiſh, but rather excite the courage of the <hi>Queen,</hi> who had alſo made ready a ſplendid Navy, well furniſhed with gallant Commanders, Sea-men, and Soldiers; and a Land-Army, where they lay encamped at <hi>Tilbury-Fort</hi> in <hi>Eſſex;</hi> there the Queen appeared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them on a white <hi>Palſrey,</hi> to their great incouragement. But when their Armado ſhould have ingaged our Fleet, God Almighty took his own way, and raiſed ſuch Storms and Winds, that their whole Forces were
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:59632:32"/> all ſcattered and deſtroyed without fighting, very few of them eſcaping to tell the news in <hi>Spain</hi> to their Lord and Maſter, and their ſurviving Friends.</p>
            <p>Now let us proceed to give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of ſome memorable actions of noble Perſons ſince that great delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tho. Stapleton,</hi> born at <hi>Henfield</hi> in <hi>Suſſ.</hi> of a very good Family; he was bred in <hi>New-College</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and became Canon of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> which place he quitted <hi>An.</hi> 1 of <hi>Eliz.</hi> and having fled beyond the Seas, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <hi>Catechiſt</hi> at <hi>Doway;</hi> which place he having diſcharged to his commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, he was preferred <hi>King's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor</hi> of Divinity in <hi>Lovain,</hi> and was 40 years together Undertaker-gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral againſt all Proteſtants. Dr. <hi>Whita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> profeſſor in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally profeſſed, That <hi>Bellarmine</hi> was the <hi>fairer,</hi> and <hi>Stapleton</hi> the <hi>ſhrew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> Adverſary. He died, and was buried in St. <hi>Peters</hi> in <hi>Lovain,</hi> 1598.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:59632:32"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Edm Spencer,</hi> born in <hi>London,</hi> bred in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> a great Poet, who imitated <hi>Chaucer:</hi> 'Tis ſaid that he preſented Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> with a Poem, with which ſhe was ſo well pleaſed, that ſhe commanded the Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer <hi>Cecil</hi> to give him 100<hi>l.</hi> and when he alleaged that Sum was too much, then give him (quoth the Q.) what is reaſon; but being delayed, he preſented theſe Lines to the Queen.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>I was promiſed on a time</l>
               <l>To have reaſon for my Rhime;</l>
               <l>From that time, unto this ſeaſon,</l>
               <l>I receiv'd nor Rhime nor Reaſon.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Hereupon the Queen gave ſtrict or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for the preſent payment of 100<hi>l.</hi> He was afterwards Secretary to the Lord <hi>Gray,</hi> Deputy of <hi>Ireland.</hi> He was an excellent Linguiſt, Antiqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Philoſopher, Mathematician; yet ſo poor (as being a Poet) that he was thought <hi>fami, non famae ſcribere.</hi> Returning into <hi>England,</hi> he was
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59632:33"/> robb'd by the Rebels of that little he had; and dying for grief in great want, 1598. was honourably buried nigh <hi>Chaucer</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of his Funeral and Monument, was defrayed at the ſole charge of <hi>Robert,</hi> firſt of that name, Earl of <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Walt. Raleigh,</hi> born at <hi>Budeley, Devonſh.</hi> of an ancient Family, but decayed in Eſtate, and he was the youngeſt Brother thereof, was bred in <hi>Ori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll</hi> College in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and thence coming to Court, found ſome hopes of the Queens favour; this made him write in a glaſs Window, obvious to the Queens Eye, <hi>Fain would I climb, yet fear I to fall.</hi> Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which, her Majeſty perceiving it, did write, <hi>If thy Heart fail thee, climb not at all.</hi> But his Introduction into Court, is ſaid to have born an elder date, from the time he ſpread his <hi>pluſh Cloak</hi> for her Majeſty to ſtep upon over a wet place: Yet the wiſe Queen in rewarding him, made him
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:59632:33"/> to purchaſe by pain and peril, as well as Complement, what places were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on him. He ſeemed to be born to that only, which he went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, ſo dextrous he was in all his undertakings, in <hi>Court,</hi> in <hi>Camp,</hi> by <hi>Sea,</hi> by <hi>Land,</hi> by <hi>Sword,</hi> by <hi>Pen;</hi> witneſs in the laſt, his <hi>Hiſtory of the World.</hi> Of his detractors, he was wont to ſay, If any Man accuſe to my face, I will anſwer him with my Mouth; but my Tail is good enough to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to ſuch who traduce me behind my back. Yet ſuch a Traducer there was, that ſubtle <hi>Gondamour,</hi> the Span. Ambaſſador to K. <hi>James,</hi> that never left his ſollicitations and intreagues with the King, till he procured his Decollation, which was done <hi>Ann.</hi> 1618. Thus died this learned and honourable Perſon, never to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, ſo long as wiſe Men are li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Bray,</hi> Tenant to Mr. <hi>Richard Carew,</hi> carried upon his back, <hi>Ann.</hi> 1608. at one time, ſix buſhels of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:59632:34"/> wheaten Meal, by the ſpace, well near a butt length, and upon the wheaten Meal the Miller, a Lubber of above 24 years of Age. And</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Roman,</hi> the <hi>Corniſh Milo,</hi> ſo uſed to Burdens in his Child-hood, that when a Man, he would bear the whole Carcaſe of an Oxe, and never tugged thereat.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tho. Sackvill,</hi> Son and Heir to Sir <hi>Richard,</hi> (Chancellor, Sub-Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of the Exchequer, and Privy-Counſellor to Q. <hi>Elizabeth,)</hi> by <hi>Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifred</hi> his Wife, Daughter to Sir <hi>John Bruges,</hi> was bred in <hi>Oxford,</hi> where he became an excellent Poet, leaving both <hi>Latine</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Poems of his compoſing to poſterity: Then he became Barriſter, and afterwards in his Travels was for ſome time pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner at <hi>Rome;</hi> whence returning to the poſſeſſion of a good Eſtate, he waſted the greateſt part thereof; and afterwards being made (as is repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) to dance attendance on an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman of <hi>London,</hi> who had gained
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:59632:34"/> great Penny-worths by his former purchaſes of him, he was ſenſible of the incivility, and reſolving to be no more beholding to <hi>wealthy Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le,</hi> he turned a thrifty improver of the remainder of his Eſtate. Others af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> (his <hi>Couſin-German</hi> once removed) diverted the torrent of his Profuſion, by her fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent admonition; after which ſhe made him Baron of <hi>Buckhurſt</hi> in <hi>Suſſ.</hi> ſent him Ambaſſador into <hi>France,</hi> then into the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> made him Knight of the <hi>Garter,</hi> and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer of <hi>England.</hi> He was Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of the Univerſity, where he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> with a ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous Feaſt. He was a perſon of ſo quick diſpatch, that his Secretarys ſeldom pleaſed him. Thus having made amends to his Houſe for his mis-ſpent time, both in increaſe of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate and Honour, being created Earl of <hi>Dorſet</hi> by K. <hi>James,</hi> He died in <hi>April, An.</hi> 1608.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:59632:35"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Tho. Bilſon,</hi> born in <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> then of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter;</hi> as Reverend and Learned a Prelate as <hi>England</hi> ever afforded, witneſs his Works of <hi>The perpetual Government of Chriſt's Church, and of Chriſt's deſcent into Hell.</hi> The new Tranſlation of the Bible was by King <hi>James</hi>'s command ultimately commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his, and Dr. <hi>Smith</hi>'s (Biſhop of <hi>Glouceſter)</hi> peruſal. He died <hi>An.</hi> 1618.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert Smith,</hi> born at <hi>Mercate-Harborough,</hi> Merchant-Taylor in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> Comptroller of the Chamber there, and one of the four Attornies of the Mayor's Court, gave 750 <hi>l.</hi> to purchaſe Lands for the maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of a Lecturer in the Town of his Nativity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as appears by the Settlement. He died <hi>An.</hi> 1618.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Tho. Coventry,</hi> born at <hi>Croon</hi> in <hi>Worceſterſhire,</hi> was eldeſt Son to Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> Knight, one of the Juſtices of the Common-Pleas. He was bred in, and Treaſurer of the Inner-Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:59632:35"/> 1618. being firſt Attorney-Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to K. <hi>James:</hi> He was afterwards made Lord-Keeper of the Great-Seal, and 1. of <hi>Charles</hi> I. by whom he was created, <hi>An.</hi> 4 <hi>Regis,</hi> Baron <hi>Coventry,</hi> of <hi>Alesborough</hi> in this County. He en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed the dignity of Lord-Keeper fifteen Years, if it was not more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to ſay, that Dignity enjoyed him. The Patent whereby he was created Baron, makes mention of his moſt worthy Services to K. <hi>James,</hi> and K. <hi>Charles;</hi> he died before the Civil Wars; never Lord-Keeper made few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Orders which were afterwards re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed, his being firmly grounded on the conſent of Parties.</p>
            <p>In this year 1618, were executed at Tyburn 19 Pirats, and one <hi>Garnet</hi> a Jeſuit.</p>
            <p>And the deſtruction of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Army ſent againſt the <hi>Venetians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Martin</hi>'s Fort relieved by the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>Schomberge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ebſham-</hi>Waters (now <hi>Epſom)</hi> found out in a dry Seaſon, the Water firſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:59632:36"/> obſerved (in a Horſe or Neats foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) run through ſome Veins of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume,</hi> and are abſterſive and ſanative, being outwardly and inwardly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Jo. Doderidg,</hi> bred in <hi>Oxford,</hi> a general Scholar, was ſecond Juſtice of the King's Bench; his Soul con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted of two Eſſentials, <hi>Ability</hi> and <hi>Integrity,</hi> holding the Scale of Juſtice with a ſteady hand. He is famous for the expreſſion, <hi>That as old and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm as he was, he would go to</hi> Tyburn <hi>on Foot, to ſee ſuch a Man hang'd, that ſhould proffer Mony for a place of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature;</hi> it being neceſſary that thoſe who buy ſuch Offices by whole-ſale, ſhould ſell Juſtice by re-tale, to make themſelves ſavers. He was common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called <hi>the ſleeping Judge,</hi> becauſe he would ſit on the Bench with his Eyes ſhut, a poſture of attention. He died, leaving no Iſſue, <hi>An.</hi> 1628. and was interred in our <hi>Lady's Chapel,</hi> in <hi>Exet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:59632:36"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Tobias Mathew,</hi> D. D. bred in <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> became Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> and at laſt of <hi>York:</hi> when placed there, he merrily ſaid, <hi>He wanted nothing but Grace:</hi> he died <hi>An.</hi> 1628.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tho. Taylor,</hi> born at <hi>York,</hi> and bred in <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s College in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into the Miniſtry at 27 years of Age, continuing in the ſame at <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> and <hi>London</hi> 35 years; a pious and charitable man, and a painful Preacher: A little before his death he avowed, <hi>That we ſerved ſuch a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter who covereth many imperfections, and giveth much Wages for a little work.</hi> He died about 1628.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note</hi> alſo, in this year 1628. Dr. <hi>Lamb</hi> was murdered in the City of <hi>London,</hi> for which the ſaid City was fined 6000 <hi>l.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nath. Shute,</hi> born at <hi>Gigleswick, Yorkſh.</hi> and bred in <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s College in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> was an excellent Schollar, and ſolid Preacher, (at St. <hi>Mildred-Poultrey</hi> in <hi>London,)</hi> though nothing of his is extant in Print, ſave a Sermon
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:59632:37"/> called <hi>Corona Charitatis:</hi> He was an <hi>uncomfortable</hi> Preacher in one ſenſe, in that he left no hope of imitation for ſuch as ſhould ſucceed him. He di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>An.</hi> 1638.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> There were four other Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to this <hi>Nath. viz. Joſiah,</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of St. <hi>Mary Woollnoth, London, Robert</hi> in <hi>Linn, Thomas</hi> in <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and <hi>Timothy</hi> in <hi>Exeter,</hi> all famous for Learning, and laborious Preachers.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Rich. Hutton,</hi> born at <hi>Perith, Cumberland,</hi> of a worſhipful Family, and bred in <hi>Jeſus</hi> College in <hi>Cambr.</hi> diverted from Divinity by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity chiefly of <hi>George,</hi> Earl of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> became Barriſter in <hi>Grays-Inn;</hi> and 'twas obſerved, he ſeldom or never took Fees of <hi>Clergy-men</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards; being Recorder of <hi>York</hi> he was Knighted, and made Judge of the Common-Pleas, and continued, though his opinion was againſt <hi>Ship-Money,</hi> the King uſing to call him the <hi>honeſt Judge:</hi> he died, and was buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at St. <hi>Dunſtan</hi>'s in the <hi>Weſt, An.</hi> 1638.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:59632:37"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Joſeph Mede,</hi> born near <hi>Biſhop-Stratford, Eſlex,</hi> wrote <hi>de Sanctitate relativa:</hi> he was a learned Man, good Preacher, and charitable to the Poor. From that place of Scripture, <hi>Judges</hi> 3. 30. <hi>And the Land had reſt eight Years,</hi> he obſerved that that was the longeſt time of Peace that the Church of God enjoyed: And ſeeing the ſame leaſe of <hi>Halcyon days</hi> was expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in <hi>England,</hi> ſince 1. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> he did grievouſly ſuſpect ſome ſtrange concuſſion in Church and State, which came to paſs accordingly. He was a <hi>Millenary,</hi> and was as much diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by ſome <hi>furious Followers,</hi> as even <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> was by <hi>ignorant Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> to his Philoſophy. He died <hi>An.</hi> 1638. leaving near 3000 <hi>l.</hi> to <hi>Chriſts</hi> College in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> where he was bred.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edm. Doubleday,</hi> Eſq; a man of great Stature, Valor, Gravity and Activity, attended Sir <hi>Tho. Knevet, Novemb.</hi> 4. 1605. when he ſearched the Cellar beneath the Parliament-Houſe,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:59632:38"/> where they found <hi>Guy Faux,</hi> with his dark Lanthorn, in the <hi>dead</hi> of the <hi>Night,</hi> providing for the death of many next Morning. He was newly come out of the <hi>Devils Cloſet,</hi> (the inner Room where the Powder lay.) <hi>Faux</hi> beginning to buſtle, Mr. <hi>Doubleday</hi> ordered him at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, up with his Heels, and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with the Traitor lay the Treaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> along the Floor, by <hi>God</hi>'s good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> detected and defeated. <hi>Faux</hi> vow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that had he been taken in the inn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Room, he had blown up himſelf and all the Company therein. Mr. <hi>Double<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> died <hi>An.</hi> 1618.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Moile,</hi> born in, or near <hi>South-Molton, Devon.</hi> bred in <hi>France,</hi> where he became perfect in the Language, ſpent his youth in Military imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and in his reduced Age, was made an Examiner in the Court of <hi>Tho.</hi> Lord <hi>Burgley,</hi> and Preſident of the <hi>North:</hi> Afterwards, being Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour to the Lord <hi>Roſs,</hi> he went to <hi>Rome</hi> with him, where that Lord
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:59632:38"/> was courted, and Mr <hi>Moile</hi> impriſoned in the Inquiſition; the Prieſts in vain hacking at the <hi>root</hi> of his <hi>conſtancy,</hi> he continued 30 years in Priſon, and died 1638. <hi>at.</hi> 81.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Salkod,</hi> a branch of a worſhipful Family, bred beyond the Seas, either <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> or <hi>ſecular Prieſt,</hi> coming over into <hi>England</hi> to <hi>angle</hi> for <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> his <hi>line</hi> broke, and he was caſt in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whence being brought to King <hi>James,</hi> by his Arguments, (with a Benefice beſtowed on him in <hi>Somerſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,)</hi> he became a Proteſtant: he was not a little proud that the King was pleaſed to ſtile him the <hi>learned Salkod.</hi> See his true Character in the Book he writ of Angels. He died <hi>An.</hi> 1638.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Benj. Johnſon,</hi> (whoſe Mother married a <hi>Brick-layer</hi> for her ſecond Husband,) was bred in <hi>Weſtminſter-School,</hi> then in St. <hi>John</hi>'s College in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> (being alſo honorary Member of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>Oxford,)</hi> where he continued but few Weeks
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:59632:39"/> for want of further Maintenance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fain to return to the trade of his Father-in-Law, he helped at the new Structure of <hi>Lincoln-Inn,</hi> when having a Trowel in his hand, he had a Book in his pocket; ſome Gentlemen after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards manumiſed him, freely to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his own ingenious Inclinations: his Wit was <hi>elaborate,</hi> wrought out by his own Induſtry; he would ſit ſilent in learned Company, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uck in (beſides Wine) their ſeveral Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors into his obſervation; he was paramount in the dramatique part of Poetry, and taught the Stage an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act conformity to the Laws of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medians; his Comedies were above the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> (which are only tickled with down-right obſcenity,) and took not ſo well at the firſt <hi>ſtroke,</hi> as at the <hi>rebound,</hi> when beheld the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time; yea, they will endure reading, and that with due commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, ſo long as either <hi>Ingenuity</hi> or <hi>Learning</hi> are faſhionable in our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: He died <hi>An.</hi> 1638, and was bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:59632:39"/> in the Abby Church of <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> under a ſmall Stone, with this Inſcription, <hi>O rare Ben. Johnſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Robert Car,</hi> Son to <hi>Thomas,</hi> Laird of <hi>Fumhurſt</hi> in the South of <hi>Scotland,</hi> (who being active for <hi>Mary,</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> was thereupon forced to fly to <hi>York,)</hi> was born in this City. 'Tis reported that his firſt making at Court, was by breaking his Leg at Tilting in <hi>London,</hi> whereby he came firſt into the cognizance of K. <hi>James,</hi> who reflected on him, whoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had been a kind of Confeſſor for the cauſe of the Queen his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; beſides, the young Gentleman had a handſom Perſon, and a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency of deſert;</hi> Honours were crowded upon him, made Baron, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcount, Earl of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> Knight of the <hi>Garter,</hi> Warden of the <hi>Cinque-Ports, &amp;c.</hi> He was a good natur'd Man, doing himſelf more hurt than any Man elſe; but yet much harm to others, <hi>viz.</hi> Sir <hi>Tho. Overbury</hi> loſt the favour of this Earl, by diſſuading
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:59632:40"/> him from keeping Company with a Lady, Wife of another Perſon of Honour, to whom afterwards he was married, her firſt Husband ſtill liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Earl of <hi>Eſſex,)</hi> and had a Child by her, a Daughter, who was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards married to a Perſon of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: but Sir <hi>Tho. Overbury,</hi> under a pretence for refuſing to be ſent Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador to <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> was ſent to the <hi>Tower,</hi> and his ſtrict reſtraint encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged his Enemies to practiſe his death, which was by Poiſon effected, for which divers were executed; the Earl had the ſentence of death, which by K. <hi>James,</hi> contrary to his word; was never executed, but gave him a leaſe of ſo many years, as a pardon for his Life; though he was baniſhed the Court, lived privately, even from the ſight of his Wife, and in much ſorrow and grief died, <hi>An.</hi> 1638.</p>
            <p>In this year 1638. <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. King of <hi>France</hi> was born, or rather <hi>per ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notam &amp; illicitam viam,</hi> by that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick and governing Cardinal ſent
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:59632:40"/> into the World to be a Plague to all <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> a ſpoiler and robber of his own Country, a troubler of the <hi>Gallican-Clergy,</hi> a great oppoſer of his <hi>Infallible Holineſs,</hi> a ſevere and cruel Tormenter of the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> firſt eating and plundering their Goods by his Booted Apoſtles, (his Dragoons,) and then unmercifully abuſing their Bodies, by Wounds, Irons, Whippings, Priſons, Famine, and Death it ſelf, but without buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al; which by us is never denied to any <hi>Roman-Catholick.</hi> He governs all his Vaſſals and Slaves, (that ſhould be his Subjects) by his will, rigour, and injuſtice; and when they have got any thing for their own Family, the King's Officers take it for their Maſter; and there is no remedy for this general contagion. But yet let me inform you of one piece of good nature that is rooted faſt to him, tho' he reſiſts the Pope, he loves the Turk, and much condemns the Emperor for fighting againſt him; and the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:59632:41"/> 
               <hi>French</hi> K. has many times lately, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured his Brother, the Turkiſh Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, That he will divert all his Enemies, (that is, all Chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) from invading his Countrey by his own powerful Armies. And pray do not think much of theſe his ſtrange and extravagant expreſſions; for he hopes as there is but one <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Heaven,</hi> ſo there will be but one on <hi>Earth,</hi> and that muſt be a <hi>French one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was alſo in this year 1638. a many little Devils (called the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanters)</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> gathered into a riotous Body, and chuſed <hi>David Leiſley</hi> for their General, and ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>France</hi> for aid; (and though it took little effect,) yet you may learn that the <hi>Scotch</hi> were always great lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> Their Covenant conſiſting of 666 words, (the mark of the Beaſt) was ſet on Foot, and every one, willing, or not, ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it down by the help of labouring Preachers, the Covenanters. All this
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:59632:41"/> was but a preparative for their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into <hi>England,</hi> which they did the next year; and according to their Covenant to ſettle the King in his Throne in Peace and Honour, and make him a Glorious King, which (contrary to their Covenant) by Perjury, falſehood, and ſelling his Perſon was accompliſhed in <hi>an.</hi> 1648. next to be obſerved, being a year full of wonder and horrour: but before we give an account of that take notice there was four perſons concerned in a Tumult in <hi>Moor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fields,</hi> pretending to reform by pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down Baudy Houſes on the <hi>Eaſter Holidays,</hi> who was ſentenced and executed as Traytors, <hi>May</hi> 9. 1638. I wiſh the Mobile in theſe our days were well informed of this late acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Now alſo in this year take in <hi>John Lilburn</hi> the Quaker, who was whipped at a Carts Tayle, in <hi>Febr.</hi> 1638.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:59632:42"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1648. At <hi>Preſton</hi> in <hi>Ander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> Duke <hi>Hamilton</hi> Aug. <hi>7th.</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred <hi>England</hi> with an Army. Moſt beheld him as one rather <hi>cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> than <hi>wiſe,</hi> yet rather <hi>wiſe</hi> than <hi>valiant:</hi> however he had Officers, <hi>what did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ken the geat of fighting, as wool as ony of oor Age.</hi> He would accept of no <hi>Engliſh</hi> aſſiſtance: Their Van and their Rear were many miles aſunder, and they met the reſiſtance of Major General <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> before they expected it. He at <hi>Preſton,</hi> gave the <hi>Scotch Army</hi> ſuch a <hi>blow</hi> as ſtunned it, though it reeled on ſome miles more South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward into <hi>Staffordſhire.</hi> Where at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lceſter</hi> the Duke was taken Priſoner and utterly defeated; and afterwards made a Priſoner in the Tower, and then condemned and executed with the Lord <hi>Capel,</hi> which is the next to be taken notice of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arthur Capel,</hi> Eſq; of <hi>Hadham Hartf.</hi> was by <hi>Ch.</hi> I. Created Baron 1641. after the ſurrender of <hi>Oxford,</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:59632:42"/> he retired to his Houſe, from whence he went to <hi>Colcheſter.</hi> His Loyalty to his Maſter was proof againſt all Batteries, and Sollicitations of his Enemies. He was ſent Priſoner to the <hi>Tower</hi> by the Parliament (which was butindeed but a part of) the <hi>Dom. Com.</hi> He eſcaped from the <hi>Tower</hi> in <hi>Feb.</hi> but was retaken and ſent back, and the next day an Act made for his Tryal, and being condemned, was behead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 1648. undaunted on the <hi>Scaffold.</hi> Hence one alluding to his Arms (a <hi>Lyon Rampant in a Field Gules betwixt three Croſſes)</hi> made theſe following Lines.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thus Lyon like</hi> Capel <hi>undaunted ſtood,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Beſet with</hi> Croſſes <hi>in a</hi> Field <hi>of</hi> Blood.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>He wrote a book of <hi>Meditation,</hi> wherein judicious Piety is diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, he was <hi>Grandfather</hi> to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Earl of <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:59632:43"/>
            <p> The Earl of <hi>Holland</hi> was executed at the ſame time with this Noble Lord <hi>Capel:</hi> and Duke <hi>Hamilton March</hi> 9th <hi>an.</hi> 1648.</p>
            <p>And now give me leave to bring in a Murder, without any former precedent, and I hope none will be ſo wicked and horrid as to think of the like fact for the future. <hi>Char.</hi> the I. our Lawful and good King was taken from his own Houſe at <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denby</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> and carried to <hi>Childerſley</hi> (by Cornet <hi>Joice)</hi> then to <hi>Royſten, Hatfield, Windſor, Hampton-Court,</hi> this was done in <hi>May</hi> and <hi>June.</hi> Then the King eſcaped to the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> but ſtay'd not long before he was brought back: and <hi>Jan.</hi> 4. an Ordinance was engroſſed, and read for the <hi>Kings Tryal, Jan.</hi> 20. he was brought before the High Court of <hi>Juſtice</hi> (falſely ſo called) 22. day the ſecond time, 23. the third time was brought before the ſaid Court; the 27. day ſentenced to Death by that bold <hi>Traitor John</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:59632:43"/> 
               <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> the 30. day barbarouſly murdred at his own Palace door, betwixt 1. and 2. a Clock. So fell this Pious and Learned Prince, who will never be too much lamented, nor forgotten. This ſad Subject would make a Volume, but that is not my intention; &amp; there are ſeveral Tracts already written. That alone of Dr. <hi>Nalſon</hi>'s of the Kings Judges under <hi>Phelp</hi>'s own hand is ſufficient: and note when the King was mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, Sir <hi>Tho. Fairfax</hi> was <hi>General,</hi> and <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi> was Leiutenant General of the Army: The latter over ruling, overawing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; over fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the former; or elſe Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi>'s Letter would have turned that vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Torrent, which with him took no effect, but was altogether ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or unregarded, but would have converted any unbjaſſed perſon from doing or ſuffering to be done ſuch a bloody and unjuſt Act, by ſo many impious Regicides. Then the above named falſe and confuſed Society
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:59632:44"/> adjourned <hi>Hilary</hi> Term. <hi>Febr.</hi> 6. the Kings Office voted unneceſſary and burdenſome, the 7. the King's body removed to <hi>Windſor,</hi> and there interred under a ſmall Marble Stone, and ſo remains to this day, without any ſhow of Magnificence or Regal Monument, (where I hope his now duſt will reſt quietly.) But before I cloſe up this fatal year, let me produce one little wonder. Note that in the <hi>Hundred of R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ckford Eſſex</hi> an Army of Mice ſhaved off all the Graſs at the bare roots, which withered to Dung, was infectious to Cattle: the <hi>March</hi> following, numberleſs flocks of <hi>Owls</hi> from all parts flew thither, and deſtroyed them, and 68 years before this year, happened the like accident in the Hundred of <hi>Dengy</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jo. Richardſon,</hi> Born in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> of a moſt worſhipful and ancient Family, bred in the Univerſity of <hi>Dublin,</hi> where he was graduated Doctor in Divinity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:59632:44"/> made Biſhop of <hi>Ardagh</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi> In the late Rebellion he came over into <hi>England,</hi> a grave man and good Divine; verifying the Rule, <hi>Bonus Texturius, Bonus Theologus,</hi> for he carried a Concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance in his memory. The larger <hi>Annotations,</hi> eſpecially on <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> an elaborate work, challenge him, in a great meaſure, for the Author. Our Biſhop who had been relieved, had his bounty to beſtow on others, and by his will bequeathed a conſiderable Legacy to the College of <hi>Dublin.</hi> He dyed <hi>an.</hi> 1658. aged 74.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jo. Cleaveland,</hi> Born at <hi>Hinkley Loic.</hi> (where his Father was Vicar) was Fellow in St. <hi>John</hi>'s College in <hi>Camb.</hi> and <hi>Advocate General</hi> in the Garriſon of <hi>Newark, a general Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, pure Latiniſt, exquiſite Orator,</hi> and <hi>eminent Poet.</hi> His lofty fancy may ſeem to ſtride from the top of one Mountain to the top of another, ſo making to it ſelf a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant <hi>champain</hi> and Level of <hi>continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:59632:45"/> elevations. He dyed <hi>an.</hi> 1658. and was buried at <hi>College Hill Church.</hi> Mr. <hi>Parſon</hi> in his funeral Sermon forbore his praiſes, ſeeing ſuch who knew him not would ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect them far above, whilſt ſuch as were acquainted with him, did know them much beneath his true deſert.</p>
            <p>In this year (58) <hi>Dunkirk</hi> was taken by the Engliſh, but not long after by the Engliſh, or by a few of the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſort of the Engliſh, ſold to the French King, and ſurrendred into his hands, and 'twas ſuch a Bargain for <hi>France,</hi> as <hi>England</hi> has had reaſon, and I am afraid ever will, to lament and be much afflicted for the loſs of it; and a hard-task it will prove to reduce it to the Crown of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this year alſo being in <hi>July,</hi> Sir <hi>H. Slingsby</hi> and the Reverend and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Dr. <hi>Huit</hi> was beheaded under the Tyranny of <hi>Oliver Cromwel:</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he ſet up a High-Court of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:59632:45"/> Juſtice (called ſo then.) Dr. <hi>Huit</hi> was a very great and good Divine, and though <hi>Oliver</hi>'s Daughter ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much beſought her Father up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her knees for his life (all was but in vain) however it was belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that the Monſter of mankind <hi>Oliver</hi> never enjoyed himſelf long after, for he was much troubled with Gravel, and a little after that, was much tormented with the Stone in the Bladder, and though Dr. <hi>Bowls</hi> ſet him on his head and his heels upwards, to remove the ſtone, and gave him ſome eaſe at preſent; yet he being return'd to his natural po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, and the Dr. into the Country with his Coach and Six, which <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> had beſtowed on him for his fees and attendance, the Stone preſſed down again with that violence and force, and cauſed that horrible pain, and that pain a Feaver, and the Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver brought that which took the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent Uſurper from his <hi>Protector<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> which happened <hi>Sept.</hi> 3. 1658.</p>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:59632:46"/>
            <p> Now let me deſire you to accept of the Company of his Son <hi>Richard</hi> for a <hi>Protector:</hi> Though he ſtaid but ſix Months at the Helm, the Sea (the Commonwealth of <hi>Engl.)</hi> grew very boiſterous and ſick, till <hi>Richard</hi> was ſpewed up, and outed of his Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorſhip. And he wanting his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Courage and Judgment, was outed accordingly; 'twas ſaid, he had ſome kindneſs for <hi>King Ch.</hi> II. and was willing to ſhew it at that time, and help to reſtore him: but too many eyes were upon him, and his own want of experience, made all ineffectuall at that juncture of affairs; and the Government was put into other hands, as ſhall appear afterwards. This ſhort-ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>Protector</hi> did very little in his half years <hi>Reign,</hi> only got together things neceſſary for his Fathers <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous</hi> Funeral, which was upon <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vomber</hi> 23. 1658. This funeral coſt ſo much, that all the Tradeſmen and others concerned in it, were ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:59632:46"/> forced to run away, or hide themſelves in ſome <hi>Alſatia</hi> ever after.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1668. In this year there were two <hi>Eaſter</hi> days, the one being in <hi>April,</hi> and the other on <hi>March</hi> 23. 1668. and the precedent year had no <hi>Eaſter.</hi> A thing to be noted, becauſe 'tis to be found very rarely, either by looking forward or the days paſt.</p>
            <p>This year alſo by inſtigation of the Parliament to the King, an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der was made to ſend the Earl of <hi>Clarendon</hi> out of <hi>England.</hi> He tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled to <hi>Montpelier</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> where he ſtayed ſome years, and then hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the joyful news of his return, with exceſs of joy gave up the ghoſt: his body was brought into <hi>England,</hi> and interred in <hi>H.</hi> 7. Chapel, cloſe by the Steps. He was the firſt Lord Chancellor under <hi>Ch.</hi> II. <hi>James</hi> Duke of <hi>York</hi> was married to his Daughter <hi>Ann</hi> at the Kings return into <hi>England:</hi> from whom are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended <hi>Mary</hi> Our Gracious Queen,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:59632:47"/> and <hi>Ann</hi> Princeſs of <hi>Denmark.</hi> The firſt ſtone of the firſt pillar of the Royal <hi>Exchange</hi> was laid by <hi>K. Ch.</hi> II. in this year 1668.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1678. In this year the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Plot was diſcovered, and 18 per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were executed for the ſame: the chief of them was Viſcount <hi>Stafford,</hi> beheaded at <hi>Towerhill. Edw. Coleman</hi> Eſq; then Secretary to the Dutcheſs of <hi>York,</hi> his Houſe ſearche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and Papers ſeized <hi>(October</hi> the 1. day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) Wherein was found ſo much of moment and matter relating to the ſubverſion of Religion and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment here eſtabliſhed, and, as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by his Tryal at large in Print, he was found guilty, and was drawn, hang<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d and quartered at <hi>Tyburn,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowing his innocence to the laſt: it may be, he expected a Pardon; for he was heard to ſay, There was no truth in Mortal Man; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, his Maſter was not ſorry for his <hi>Exit, tam cito.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard Langhorn</hi> Eſq; a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:59632:47"/> committed to <hi>Newgate</hi> upon the ſame account, and ſuffered after the ſame manner. Mr. <hi>Staly</hi> the Goldſmith in <hi>Covent Garden,</hi> for ſpeaking ſome Treaſonable words, ſuffered after the ſame manner. <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Grove</hi> were alſo exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted at <hi>Tyburn,</hi> and afterwards ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Prieſts, as <hi>Gavan, Whitebread, Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Plunket,</hi> and others executed. Alſo <hi>Harecourt,</hi> and <hi>Blundel.</hi> In <hi>Oct.</hi> Ld. <hi>Wil. Powis, Howard</hi> Viſcount <hi>Stafford,</hi> Lord <hi>Arundel</hi> of <hi>Wardour,</hi> Lord <hi>Petre, John</hi> Lord <hi>Bellaſis</hi> ſurrendred them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, are ſent to the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> where Lord <hi>Petre</hi> dyed. Viſcount <hi>Stafford</hi> was beheaded on <hi>Tower-hill,</hi> and after ſome years, the reſt by the bold Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Jefferies</hi> (when all other Judges r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fuſed) was bayled out Of whoſe cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter and carriage you may ſee more in 88. following.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Septemb.</hi> in this year 1678. <hi>Titus Otes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> ſwears to his information be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey.</hi> On the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:59632:48"/> 
               <hi>28th.</hi> Dr. <hi>Tong, Kirby,</hi> and <hi>T. Otes</hi> diſcover the Plot to the Privy Council: For <hi>Tong</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> there were aſſigned very good lodgings in <hi>Whitehall,</hi> a ſtrong Guard, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſhes of Meat, and a very conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Penſion; however it was not pleaſing enough to <hi>Otes,</hi> for in <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary</hi> after, he tells the Lords in plain terms, that if they will not help him to more money, he muſt be forced to help himſelf; he was a man of a haughty ſpirit and great conſidence; but his knowledge and honeſty were beſt made known by his Narratives, and ſeveral exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations before the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; and at the Tryals and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnations of ſeveral perſons who ſuffered death, as you read be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this preſent year. And it was obſerved when he went before the Houſe of Commons or any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee whatſoever, when he had pump'd himſelf dry, he would tell them, his memory would not ſerve
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:59632:48"/> him any longer at that time; and then at the next time of his appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, he would deſcend to the bottom of the Plot, and bring new matter every time to be regiſtred for the belief of future Ages. But after ſome few months, there came in ſomany new Diſcoverers (finding good acceptance) into the <hi>Plot-Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> as did a little abate the reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the old ones, viz. <hi>Dugdale, Bedloe, Bolron, Mawbry, Comins, Allen, Dangerſield, Zeal, Boice, Prance, Jennings, Everard, Turbervile,</hi> young <hi>Tong, Smith;</hi> Iriſh Evidences, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe would meet by couples or ſometimes more, and upon ſome queſtions, interrogatories and debates that would ariſe amongſt them, things of ſmall matter of moment would be made great; and impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babilities made plain truths. Some pieces were made up and brought to perfection, and ſome laid by, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they could not be hammered out according to their intentions. For
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:59632:49"/> the King and Council finding out ſome of their deſigns in going too high in their diſcoveries, thought it high time to turn the torrent of their ſwift and ambitious proceedings, and ſo by degrees they dwindled away. And now I muſt bring to your memory, the moſt ſad and ſtrange murder of Sir <hi>Edmundbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Godfrey,</hi> a Gentleman of a very competent Eſtate, and in Commiſſion for the Peace in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> and <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſex,</hi> was reſpected by the King, beloved by his Neighbours, for his Government in the Pariſh, and his many works of Charity largely and freely diſtributed to the poor and diſtreſſed, in St. <hi>Martins</hi> in the Feilds. Being wanting four days from his Houſe in <hi>Harts-horn</hi> Lane, a great noiſe and rumour there was ſpread abroad, and great ſearch made for him, but to no purpoſe, till <hi>Octber</hi> 21. 6. days after his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, one <hi>Broomwell</hi> a Baker, and another with him a Blackſmith, both
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:59632:49"/> of St. <hi>Giles</hi> in the Feilds, coming by accident into Primroſe-hill, two miles diſtant from his own Houſe, they found his body in a ſitting poſture in a ſmall Ditch, and his own Sword run through it, his Hat and Gloves laid not far from him: the two perſons aboveſaid gave notice to the Neighbourhood, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> No Actors in this Murder as yet could be diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, The King. <hi>(Car.</hi> II.) was pleaſed to iſſue out a Proclamation promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a pardon and 500<hi>l.</hi> to any that ſhould come and make known this bloody fact; this reward of 500<hi>l.</hi> put ſome heat into Mr. <hi>Wrenn,</hi> who applies himſelf to <hi>Bedloe,</hi> and tells him one <hi>Miles Prance</hi> a Silverſmith in <hi>Prince</hi>'s Street was wanting, and he believed he was one of the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers of Sir <hi>Edmundb. Godfrey.</hi> Theſe two agreed to divide the 500<hi>l.</hi> and <hi>Bedloe</hi> preſently ſets up for a diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer, and informs the Privy Council againſt <hi>Prance,</hi> who being taken and carried before the King and Council,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:59632:50"/> owns himſelf guilty, and was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to <hi>Newgate.</hi> After a little time he denies it, and ſaid he knew nothing of the murder. The King ſends for <hi>Prance,</hi> and took him into his Cloſet, and told him, if he would tell him the truth, he would pardon him; if otherwiſe he ſhould certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be hang'd (theſe words<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I had from <hi>Prance</hi>'s own mouth) upon which ſaying of his Majeſty, <hi>Prance</hi> upon his Knees told the King what he had at firſt confeſſed to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil was true, that he was guilty with the reſt, naming <hi>Robert Green, Henry Berry, Laurence Hill,</hi> that they murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him by the Watergate in <hi>Somer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet-Houſe,</hi> carrying his body into Dr. <hi>Goden</hi>'s Chamber for five days. Then they put his Body into a Chair, and <hi>Prance</hi> and another were the firſt that carried him away, they ſet him down in the Piazza's in <hi>Covent Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> then two others took it up, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing two Prieſts, <hi>Kelly</hi> and <hi>Fitzge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rald,</hi>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:59632:50"/> and carried it to the <hi>Sohoe,</hi> where they left the Chair amongſt the buildings, and <hi>Green</hi> brought a Horſe, whereupon his body was ſet, and <hi>Hill</hi> behind it, the two Prieſts on each ſide to guide it: thus they carried it to <hi>Primroſe-hill,</hi> and left it upon that ſpot of ground, where it was found. Thus far this relation came out of <hi>Prance</hi>'s Mouth to the writer hereof ſeveral times, and he would needs carry me one day to <hi>Primroſe-hill</hi> to ſhew me the place where the body was left. Thoſe that are not ſatisfied with this, let them read his firſt and ſecond Narrative, which give more particulars, and more at large.</p>
            <p>But let us look back to ſee what the Coroners Jury did; <hi>ſuper viſum corporis</hi> two judicious Chirugeons, Mr. <hi>Skelhorn</hi> and Mr. <hi>Cambridge</hi> gave in their Opinions, that Sir <hi>Edmund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury Godfrey</hi> was murdered, his neck being broken, and beaten alſo upon
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:59632:51"/> his breaſt with ſome obtuſe weapons, and upon this and ſome other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars the Jury brought in their verdict <hi>Murder,</hi> but the Murderers then was not diſcovered. Now let us return to <hi>Prance,</hi> and take notice of his firſt Confeſſion, and the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of it. <hi>Green, Perry,</hi> and <hi>Hill</hi> were all apprehended, examined, and committed to <hi>Newgate,</hi> and at their Tryal, upon <hi>Prance</hi>'s Oath and Evidence againſt them they were found guilty of the murder of Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey,</hi> and upon <hi>Feb.</hi> 8. 1678. were executed, all living and dying Papiſts. Now obſerve in all this, his own Sword that was thruſt through his Body, was never mentioned as the cauſe of his death, for if that Sword had been made a party by the <hi>Owner,</hi> it would have equalized the Romances of St. <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis</hi> and St. <hi>Winifrid.</hi> Now remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber alſo that <hi>Kelly</hi> and <hi>Fitzgerald</hi> the two Prieſts were at the murder;
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:59632:51"/> and they would have run Sir <hi>Edm.</hi> through with their own Sword, in <hi>Somerſet-Houſe,</hi> but the other Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides would not ſuffer them; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Blood would be a means to diſcover them. And the aboveſaid Mr. <hi>Fitzgerald,</hi> ſoon after the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſaid, in the hearing of Mrs. <hi>James,</hi> then living in <hi>Katherine-Stree, That the</hi> PAPISTS <hi>had mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Sir</hi> Edmondbury Godfrey, <hi>and that it would be their deſtruction.</hi> And when Mr. <hi>Edward Coleman</hi> heard of the ſame Murder, he ſtruck his hand on his Breaſt, with theſe words, <hi>Then we are undone.</hi> And now to bring this relation to a period, I ſhall only add, That <hi>Prance</hi> always told me, for many years, That what he had ſo oft declared to me of that murder, was true; and that he would juſtifie it to the laſt drop of his blood. And here we muſt leave him, being now turned. <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> till 88, where you may find him a <hi>Papiſt</hi> again.</p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:59632:52"/>
            <p> But to proceed, the Houſe deſired the King to give <hi>Bedloe</hi> the 500<hi>l.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for his diſcovery, which Mr. <hi>Wrenn</hi> had, not long before, put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his head. Capt. <hi>Bedloe</hi> gets the Mony, but contrary to agreement of dividing it betwixt them, the Capt. would not give one crum of comfort to the <hi>Wrenn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There were alſo, in this year, ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Gentlemen, and others, impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Country, and ſome brought to <hi>London,</hi> to ſee the <hi>Tower;</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they neither ſuffered death, nor were Fined, we ſhall paſs them, and come to a year of more ſtrangeneſs and wonder than this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno.</hi> 1688. This year is uſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in with ſo much wonder, that if it be ſet down here for a real Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, not one of a Thouſand will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it; however, it muſt be left to every ones own choice. Upon the great hopes of the Queen's concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the King orders ſome of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:59632:52"/> to make an Order of <hi>Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving,</hi> in behalf of the King, the Q. and the Royal Family, upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of the Queen's being with Child; which was performed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly throughout <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then followed, by the inſtigation of the Prieſts and Papiſts to the King, a Proclamation was procured for the reading a Declaration <hi>(for Liberty of Conſcience)</hi> in all Churches and Chapels in <hi>England:</hi> This pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved very unhappy to the King, in diſguſting his beſt Subjects, the Church of <hi>England;</hi> nay, almoſt the generality of the <hi>Non-Cons</hi> did not approve of it: The <hi>Romans</hi> did uſe their utmoſt endeavours to promote it, knowing thereby their Religion would be introduced, and extirpate all but their own: the Quakers and Anabaptiſts did run with the ſtream; and <hi>Will. Penn,</hi> the Quakers chief Illuminator, was a daily Sollicitor to the King, and Father <hi>Peters</hi> his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:59632:53"/> Prieſt, for <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King, or at leaſt the Prieſts, being not ſatisfied, brought the King to put forth a ſecond Declaration to the ſame purpoſe: All the Clergy (except ſome few ignorant, and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhly affected,) ſtoutly refuſed to read the ſaid Declaration. The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops alſo had a Conference about it, and not finding it conſentaneous to their Conſciences, but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, would open the door to let in all Hereſies and Irreligion; and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhould have been ſettled in <hi>England,</hi> but <hi>Slavery, Popery,</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty.</hi> The Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> being Dr. <hi>William Sancroft,</hi> Dr. <hi>Kenn,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells,</hi> Dr. <hi>Lloyd,</hi> Biſhop of St. <hi>Aſaph,</hi> Dr. <hi>White,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Peterborough,</hi> Dr. <hi>Lak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> Sir <hi>John Trelauny,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> Dr. <hi>Turner,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ely</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:59632:53"/>
            <p> Theſe ſeven Biſhops, on the <hi>8th.</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> applied themſelves to His Majeſty, by way of an humble Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, to let him underſtand, They could not ſafely, and with a good Conſcience, ſuffer the Clergy in their ſeveral Dioceſes, to read the ſaid Declaration. The King enraged at this, the ſaid Biſhops were all ſent to the <hi>Tower,</hi> and there remained Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; their Crime being a pretended ſcandalous Petition to the King, To let him know they could not read the ſaid Declaration, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And there they remained to the <hi>15th.</hi> day of <hi>June,</hi> and then was called to the <hi>King</hi>'s<hi>-Bench-Bar,</hi> and upon their own recognizance, upon 100 <hi>l.</hi> a piece was <hi>Bailed,</hi> to appear 14 days after; upon which day, being the <hi>29th.</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> a Jury being ſworn, the <hi>Indictment</hi> read, and argued on both ſides by the learned Counſel for ſeveral hours, the <hi>Verdict</hi> was brought in <hi>Not Guilty,</hi> to the great encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:59632:54"/> and comfort of good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and for levelling the pride and inſolence of the haughty Papiſts, and their adherents.</p>
            <p>And now 19 <hi>days</hi> before this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Verdict had delivered the Biſhops from their Priſons; I ſuppoſe you expect to hear of another delivery, that is, what became of the Queen's Concept—: Now I muſt beg of you this favour, <hi>to remember,</hi> that if the Concept—was not <hi>believed,</hi> the <hi>Birth</hi> will be as little <hi>credited;</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, we had it by <hi>Tradition,</hi> as Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts have moſt of their Religion, whether Articles of Faith, or mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and form of Worſhip; and ſo are impoſed upon eaſie Believers: But if you will be ſo careful to go to find out the Pope's Infallibility; the inerrability of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; the Supremacy of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors; pardons for ſin at a cheap rate; the exact time of blowing up the Fire of Purgatory; praying to Saints
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:59632:54"/> long ſince departed; but a moiety of the Sacrament to the lay People; worſhipping of Images, <hi>cum multis aliis</hi> ſuch-like <hi>improbable Follies;</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all your pains and enquiries, be forced to take all upon truſt, and without any plain <hi>mathematical de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration,</hi> ſit down with an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit Faith, and believe, as the <hi>Church</hi> believes, not contradicting their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port; for as there was a reſolute par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty did believe, and did alſo publiſh it abroad, after the murder of Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey</hi> committed by others, he was his own <hi>ſelo de ſe,</hi> by ſheathing his <hi>own Sword</hi> in his <hi>own Body;</hi> yet how far that was congru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to reaſon, let the diſcreet man give <hi>ſentence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, after this digreſſion, you may underſtand, that there was upon the <hi>10th.</hi> of <hi>June, Anno</hi> 1688. <hi>(<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> day long before appointed, and very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely too, for that purpoſe,)</hi> a Man-child brought forth into the preſence
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:59632:55"/> of many perſons of great Quality, (but of the implicit Faith) Madam <hi>Wicks</hi> the Mid-wife, or Woman of Honour, being a knowing Artiſt, and well inſtructed in ſuch affairs, gave to every one of her own perſwaſion a full and ſatisfactory account of the whole matter, from the very begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the end, That <hi>He was the true product of the—forementioned con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception;</hi> and that God by the earneſt interceſſion of the bleſſed Lady, had heard their Prayers, and granted their deſires, in ſending them a Son; and, indeed, they knew it was a Son, before the <hi>10th.</hi> day of <hi>June,</hi> above-mentioned; now this tradition was handed about to the great, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed all places in <hi>England,</hi> by Letters, and otherways: And yet, for all this ſpecious and gilded information, if you would certainly know the truth of this great <hi>birth</hi> and <hi>ſtate,</hi> you will be forced to take their tradition, and <hi>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lieve it, as they believe it,</hi> be it <hi>true,</hi>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:59632:55"/> or <hi>not true;</hi> yet, as I ſaid before, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one is left to his own choice: For if this blind huddled buſineſs ſhould have been acted more in the light, and in the preſence of Her Royal Highneſs, the Princeſs <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> and other perſons of quality, of the <hi>Princeſs</hi>'s <hi>Religion,</hi> it would have given full-ſatisfaction to all, the now unſettled, doubtful, wavering, and ever-disbelieving Perſons of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and ſettled a firm belief upon future <hi>Generations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King, ſoon after great r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings, and illuminations for t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w <hi>Deodatus,</hi> perceiving, at a diſtance, a great ſtorm ariſing in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies himſelf to raiſe ſeveral n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of Horſe, Dragoons, and Foot; and ſends to the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> then Governour of <hi>Ireland,</hi> for 4000 or more, of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Foot, which was ſent accordingly into <hi>England;</hi> very likely, and able, and war-like Men, and coming up to <hi>London,</hi> was very
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:59632:56"/> well approved of by all the King's Officers, but the Inhabitants had a prejudice againſt them, for the <hi>Iriſh</hi> had got an ill name, and was not well ſpoken of; (though to do them Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice) in part of <hi>London,</hi> and in the City of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> they carried themſelves very civilly in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Quarters. Now it was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the Politicians of War, that theſe <hi>Iriſh,</hi> ſent out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> from the adjacent parts of <hi>Londonderry,</hi> did ſo much comfort and encourage that City, as to make it hold out ſo long, and to that extremity; and if that 4000 ſo detached, had remained in <hi>Ireland,</hi> that City, in all probability and reaſon, had been either taken, or ſurrendred to the late King <hi>James;</hi> who in this Summer 88, had formed a Campaigne on <hi>Hounſloe-heath,</hi> Horſe and Foot, to the number of betwixt 16, or 18000. where we muſt leave them at preſent, in their Tents, with their ſeveral pieces of Canon, and take
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:59632:56"/> notice how the King was equipping his Ships at Sea, to make a formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Fleet, and made choice of the Lord <hi>Dartmouth,</hi> as a chief Officer to muſter up his Seamen, for moſt of them had a great kindneſs for that Lord, who made it his buſineſs, and gathered up many Seamen, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a little time manned out ſeveral Ships to Sea; but in this time the poor Seamen, being as it were ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on board, and knew not what cauſe they were to fight for, they begun by degrees to conſider, and at laſt take the boldneſs upon them to ask their Captains, upon what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign they were upon, and who they muſt encounter withal. The Captains gave them ſuch dark and aenigmatical anſwers, as gave them no ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction: Upon which ſome of the Ships whole Crew came upon the Decks, and, as one man, told their ſeveral Officers, That they would not fight for the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> but always
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:59632:57"/> ſtand for, and maintain the <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion.</hi> Which unhappy news for King <hi>James,</hi> was carried to him by the Lord <hi>Dartmouth.</hi> The King was much diſcompoſed with the hearing thereof, but made no great outward appearance about it at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
            <p>The King's next deſign was to take off the <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> and <hi>Teſt,</hi> and for that purpoſe a <hi>Parliament</hi> was to be called to ſit at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> and many crafty Courtiers, being <hi>Papiſts,</hi> or ſo inclined, was, with ſuitable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, ſent down into the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Countys and Burroughs of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> to prepare ſuch Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers as would throw over-board the <hi>Teſt and Penal Laws</hi> at one ſitting; but this took as little effect as the former, for the King hearing by his Agitators in the Country, how that they could not make a party there prevalent enough to throw down the two <hi>Bulwarks,</hi> it ſo was ordered, that
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:59632:57"/> the deſigned <hi>Parliament</hi> never me together.</p>
            <p>Then the King's Council, where Father <hi>Peters</hi> was always of the <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> put the King himſelf to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine thoſe of his menial Servants, and thoſe that held Offices under His Majeſty, as the Great Seal, Privy Seal, Secretaries of State, Mr. Attorney, and Mr. Sollicitor-General, the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the <hi>Green Cloth,</hi> and all the Officers in <hi>White-Hall,</hi> the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners of the Cuſtoms and Fire-hearths; theſe, and many others, were all to give an account of their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſt,</hi> and then being Cloſeted by the King, they gave in their private verdict in that place; if they would not condeſcend to take away the two aforeſaid <hi>Bars,</hi> their Offices and Preferments was <hi>ipſo facto</hi> taken from them. By this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly practice many Lords, and Gentlemen, and many other inferior Officers, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> caſhiered, and many of the red <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:59632:58"/> men ſubſtituted in their places: but in all this the King gained but little ground, for the number obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and the diſobliged, were ſtill e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual.</p>
            <p>Yet they would not let the King reſt here, but they perſuade him to cloſet all his Judges of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> which accordingly he did, and found ſome of them according to his wiſh; the reſt ſtoutly oppoſed, and was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently diſplaced, and ſome mean Lawyers, and mean Perſons, but Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, or popiſhly affected, mounted up into their ſeats, at the ſeveral Courts in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Hall. By this project the King loſt the hearts of his Subjects, for theſe new Judges were ſo mean in birth, ſome in breeding, ſome in learning, and all of them ignorant of the Law; ſo that by their illiterate practice the Law was quite buried. For Sir <hi>John Maynard,</hi> that old Serjeant of the Law, told King <hi>William,</hi> That if His Majeſty had not
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:59632:58"/> come, as he had out-lived many <hi>good Lawyers,</hi> ſo he ſhould have out-lived the <hi>Law it ſelf:</hi> And the reaſon was plain, for theſe new erected Judges, did all agree in this maxime, That any penal, or ſtatute Law, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and though made and confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the three Eſtates, yet the King, by vertue of his Prerogative Royal, had power to diſpence with it; and what is that diſpenſation, but by the arbitrary will and pleaſure of the Prince, all Laws are abrogated, and all penalties thereof remitted. And the King taking theſe Judges opinion in this matter, for good Law, upon this falſe bottom, the King offered to admit, and many Zealots accepted places both Military and Civil, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking the <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Teſt,</hi> and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one under that circumſtance is liable to pay 500<hi>l.</hi> And hereby all Corporations was new transformed, Papiſts made Mayors and Aldermen, Governours of the Forts and Caſtle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:59632:59"/> Captains at Sea, Colonels, and other Officers of Land-Forces. <hi>Obadiah Walker</hi> ſet up ſome few weak Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes at <hi>Oxford,</hi> in deſpite of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; and, indeed, the Tempeſt did ariſe higher, for <hi>Magdalen College</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to admit ſome perſons by <hi>Mandamus</hi> from the King, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Law, and the Statutes of their College, were ejected themſelves, <hi>viz.</hi> Dr. <hi>Hough,</hi> Dr. <hi>Fairfax, &amp;c. Magdalen College</hi> at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> had alſo part of the ſtorm; for not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting by <hi>Mandamus,</hi> whereby Dr. <hi>Peachel,</hi> then <hi>Vice Chancell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r,</hi> was ſuſpended, <hi>ex beneficio,</hi> during the King's pleaſure, being then either <hi>Preſident,</hi> or <hi>Maſter:</hi> Some Clergy were alſo preſerred to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſhopricks, <hi>viz.</hi> Dr. <hi>Parker</hi> to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſhop of <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> Dr. <hi>Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſon,</hi> biſhop of <hi>Bangor,</hi> Dr. <hi>Cartwright,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> by the King's Diſpenſation, not taking the Oaths and Teſt. By theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples you may plainly perceive,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:59632:59"/> that the Law was perfectly buried. Not omitting the Reverend <hi>Henry Compton,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> who was by an arbitrary, and unjuſt ſentence, ſuſpended, <hi>ex officio,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Canon and Civil Law; and Dr. <hi>Sharp,</hi> Dean of <hi>Norwich,</hi> and Vicar of St. <hi>Giles</hi>'s <hi>in the Fields,</hi> was ſilenced from Preaching, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any form of Law; but indeed was willing to obey his <hi>Ordinarie,</hi> and ſo ceaſed <hi>pro tempore,</hi> in his Miniſterial Function.</p>
            <p>In this Year alſo, the Pope was pleaſed to ſend over into <hi>England</hi> his <hi>Nunci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> Count <hi>Dada,</hi> a <hi>Venetian,</hi> a man of great Abilities, and a come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Perſon, being very graciouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the King, and highly trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Courtiers, well reſpected by the Ladies of the greateſt quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and by the ignorant Bigots ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired and adored, and the more, by reaſon here had not been one reſident among us for above a hundred years,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:59632:60"/> before this time; for the Law is very ſevere both in receiving or treating any of that nomination: and if an act of Grace had not obliterated moſt Offences, that great Entertainment in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity of <hi>London,</hi> and ſeveral other miſcarriages, by ſeveral perſons of good note, had been deeply pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. Theſe are the moſt remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able paſſages which happened in this part of the year, being the latter end of <hi>September,</hi> and part of <hi>October;</hi> and now ſee what follows after.</p>
            <p>And for that purpoſe, pray recall to mind that I told you in ſome few precedent Pages, That the King per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a great Storm ariſing in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and by this time it was got o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the <hi>Pampus</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Seas, and upon the <hi>Downs,</hi> and ſo was driven on all along upon our Coaſts by <hi>Dover,</hi> and <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> and other Ports, 'till it ſafely alighted, or indeed arrived at <hi>Torbay,</hi> not many Miles diſtant from the City of <hi>Exeter,</hi> upon
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:59632:60"/> the <hi>5th.</hi> of <hi>November;</hi> and though it was eſteemed, and called a ſtorm by ſome few, yet it was a moſt joyful and golden Shower to moſt People of <hi>England;</hi> and as that day was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly noted under God's great Mercy and Goodneſs, to deliver us from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction intended, by that horrid <hi>Powder Plot:</hi> This day now will make <hi>England</hi> truly ſenſible, that by the ſame infinite goodneſs, we are made free from the ſlavery of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Arbitrary Government, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other imminent Judgments, which would undoubtedly have fallen upon us.</p>
            <p>And now let me tell you what this happy and joyful arrival was, and firſt it produced that <hi>Magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, Heroick, Noble, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndaunted, Martial</hi> and <hi>Victorious William Naſſau,</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and <hi>Stadtholder</hi> of <hi>Holland.</hi> The Forces that landed with him were as follow, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:59632:61"/>
            <p> Foot 10692. Horſe 3660<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> In all 14352.</p>
            <p>Ships, being Men of War, of the ſecond and third rate, 65. Flyboats 500. Pinks 60. Fire-ſhips 10. In all 635.</p>
            <p>This Fleet and Army, through the coldneſs of the late ſeaſon of the year, their long Voyage by adverſe Winds, upon the Sea, and perhaps the Prince's firſt intention to have landed in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part of the Kingdom, had ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſome loſs, and was much weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and weakned, and many was ſick, yet was forced to wade through the Water, to ſome conſiderable deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, at their Landing. After which the Prince was pleaſed to march to <hi>Exeter,</hi> for his head Quarters, the whole Army being there, or very near it, and it being a large and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful City, ſufficient Proviſions was made for the Prince, and all his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; the Prince ſtayed there ſome Days, expecting hourly, with great
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:59632:61"/> impatience what Nobility, Gentry Gentry and other Forces would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort to him, and join with his Army: after ſome few days, before his hopes was quite withered, there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in his Royal Preſence, the Lord <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> the Lord <hi>Cornbury,</hi> &amp;c. Colonel <hi>Godfrey</hi> and others; and by degrees ſeveral other Lords and Gentlemen, who carried along with them very good and effectual men, to augment the Army; and as the Prince advanced, his Army increaſed. This news came preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to King <hi>James</hi> from the firſt land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, who was daily and hourly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely informed of their ſeveral Movements and Advances toward what places. But the main deſign of the Prince was b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lieved by all for <hi>London,</hi> which ſell out accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</p>
            <p>The King in the junctu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of theſe affairs was in gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at amaſement; for ſome of his Army, nay ſome of his
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:59632:62"/> Life-Guard had deſerted, and went over to the Prince; yet the King truſted to his Army, eſpecially to the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> the reſt being <hi>Engliſh,</hi> ſome <hi>Scotch</hi> and ſome few <hi>French,</hi> being all muſtred together with ſeveral Trains of Artillery drawn out of the <hi>Tower;</hi> and in a Martial manner marched away on the Roads towards their Enemies: the Prince likewiſe doing the ſame in hopes to encounter with them after a little marching; but in his marching, the Prince was pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to put forth ſeveral Declarations, whereby the end and intentions of the Prince's coming into <hi>England</hi> with his Army was fairly and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcovered to the people, and with ſuch ſatisfactory reaſons there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in inſerted, that all on a ſudden the people deſired his Royal preſence, eſpecially in <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> both being places convenient to turn the Tyde of Affairs, if there had been any occaſion. Within ſix days the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:59632:62"/> Kings Army was marched to <hi>Saliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> the chief Rendezvouz, the Princes Army being about 20 or 30 miles diſtant from them; and there happened betwixt ſeveral of their Parties and Forlorn-hopes ſome ſmall encounters and skirmiſhes, but very few taken or ſlain of either ſide; the Kings Army or at leaſt the main Body lay ſtill at and about <hi>Sarum;</hi> the Princes Army drawing nearer to that place, inſomuch that the King daily expected a Battle; but on a ſudden the Scene was changed; for a Rumour only coming to the King, that the Prince's Army was ready at hand to fall upon his, the King forthwith without calling a Council of War, or any other conſideration, left them in great haſt and diſorder, and returned to <hi>London:</hi> the Army being thus deſerted by the King; whether for want of a good Cauſe, for the love they bore to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, or their good will
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:59632:63"/> and opinion for the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> Beſides, an Order given to the Earl of <hi>Feverſham</hi> for their Disbanding, the great expected Battel was ended be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it begun, the Kings Army flying away, or at the beſt eaſily retreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when no enemy purſued after them; it ſeemeth they had read or at leaſt heard of Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi>'s <hi>ſelf-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſuppoſed terrible Army being removed, leaving the Roads very clear and quiet, for the Prince's Horſe to march at their leiſure, and come for <hi>London,</hi> which by eaſie Marches in few days was accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, to the great joy and rejoying of <hi>England.</hi> But before his Highneſs would arrive at <hi>White-hall,</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent diſorders by tumults or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, which might have been raiſed by the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> and other diſaffected perſons reſiding, and buſying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in and about <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> he was pleaſed to ſend three or
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:59632:63"/> more Lords to the King, that he would be pleaſed to withdraw his perſon, and his Guards to <hi>Windſor,</hi> or any other place, where his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty ſhould make choice of. And withall upon the <hi>word</hi> of a <hi>Prince</hi> his Majeſty ſhould be ſecured from all fear and danger. This meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage came to the King about 11. or 12. a Clock in the Night, which being delivered, the King preſently prepared himſelf, and withdrew into <hi>Kent,</hi> with a party of his Guards to <hi>Rocheſter.</hi> This was his firſt leaving <hi>White-hall, December 10th,</hi> and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Feverſham</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken and brought back to <hi>London</hi> in great ſtate, and rejoycing by his Subjects, and the Prince did appoint ſome of his own Guards, half Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants and half Papiſts, which lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter went to Maſs with him, and had liberty to go where he pleaſed; the Guard being charged by the Prince to that very purpoſe. The <hi>Prieſts</hi>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:59632:64"/> thinking themſelves in a ſnare, (which indeed did of right belong to them) made the King very uneaſie, and perſwaded him to go away a ſecond time, which was done 18. <hi>Decemb.</hi> and going into <hi>Kent</hi> with his Guards which the King himſelf commanded, took ſhipping with a party with him, diſmiſſing his Guards; whom by gratuities he requited, and ſo ſailed into <hi>France</hi> without any diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance. Now let any indifferent and unbyaſſed perſon judge if the King was forced by any rough or unmannerly means or actions to leave his Kingdom, being upon 23. of <hi>December.</hi> His <hi>Queen</hi> with her new found out Relation went away from <hi>White-hall,</hi> upon <hi>Decemb.</hi> 9. accompanied with Count <hi>Dada,</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Peters</hi> and ſome Ladies of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and Gentlewomen to wait upon her perſon, with good ſtore of Houſehold-goods, Jewels and Treaſure; and alſo landed ſafely in
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:59632:64"/> 
               <hi>France,</hi> where the French King was pleaſed after his compliments paſſed, to provide for her according to her Royal quality.</p>
            <p>The King going away, as I told you upon the 18. day. Upon the ſame day the Prince entred into St. <hi>James</hi> Palace: his whole Army marching with him increaſed by this time to above 20000, and being very much wearied by their long marches, and the winter Seaſon, was all (except ſufficient Guards) ſent into winter Quarters, into the adjacent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but eſpecially <hi>Southwark, Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> and the Suburbs were filled with ſufficient numbers of them.</p>
            <p>The Army being thus provided with Quarters, the Prince was pleaſed to aſſemble a General Council conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Lords Spiritual and Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, Gentlemen, and Lawyers, in which Aſſembly the Prince was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to ſend out his ſeveral Precepts to all Counties, Cities and Borough-Towns,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:59632:65"/> in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales:</hi> theſe precepts was directed to the ſeveral Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roners in their reſpective Counties (for at this time the Sheriffs of moſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties were not ſetled) and as theſe Coroners, ſo the Mayors and Sheriffs of Cities and divers Corporations were required to give notice to all in their ſeveral Juriſdictions at cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain days prefixed, and at ſuch places as they ſhould judge convenient, and there to make choice of Able Perſons, and Gentlemen of known integrity, to appear ſuch a day at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> two Houſes of Parliament, which accordingly was performed, and received the <hi>Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> of a <hi>Convention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fore this meeting, the Prince was pleaſed to ſend for over into <hi>England</hi> his <hi>Royal Conſort</hi> Mary <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of</hi> Orange; this <hi>Convention</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome weeks, taking into conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration the diſtracted and unſetled condition of the Nation, wanting
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:59632:65"/> a Head, and power to reſtore the ſaid Nation into its priſtine Glory and Safety, by the advice of the beſt Lawyers and Stateſmen, and by ſearch of many former Precedents, wherein it did plainly appear, that in all reaſon, this Convention ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally choſen by the conſent of the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> might be ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Parliament of England</hi> to all intents and purpoſes. And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, under that denomination, all matters of State, and concerns of the Publick, were tranſacted.</p>
            <p>And taking into their conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the departure of King <hi>James</hi> out of the Kingdom, after many argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con.</hi> it was agreed, that by ſuch departure out of the Kingdom, without any compulſion, but his own free accord, he had abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely <hi>abdicated</hi> his <hi>Kingdom;</hi> and it was abſolutely neceſſary, the Crown ſhould be conferred on the next law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Heir,</hi> which was, without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:59632:66"/> arguing, adjudged to be <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry</hi> Princeſs of <hi>Orange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs the Parliament, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſearching into the State of the Kingdom, into what great dangers it was relapſed, both by reaſon of open Enemies and ſeeming boſom-Friends at home, the Deviliſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treagues of that deadly hater of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and almoſt all Mankind, <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>French King;</hi> for preventing theſe miſchievous deſigns now on Foot againſt <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> it was Voted by Both <hi>Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parliament, Nemine contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cente,</hi> that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> ſhould be inveſted in the Crown, with his Lady, and ſo made King and Queen of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> with all other Dominions thereunto belonging, and they were immediately Proclaimed at <hi>Whitehall-Gate, Temple-Bar,</hi> and the <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> with the uſual Solemnities, and with great ſigns
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:59632:66"/> of rejoycing and ſatisfaction to all ſober People; and then Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were ſent down into all the Counties of <hi>England</hi> to the ſame purpoſe, which was performed with great joy and alacrity, as appeared by their many Bonſires, Ringing of Bells, and ſeveral other demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of gladneſs: they would take up ſeveral Sheets of Paper if they were to be fully mentioned in this ſmall Treatiſe; and for the Coronation of this bleſſed Pair, it falls not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my figure. Yet I hope the Readers Patience will hold out till <hi>April 11th,</hi> in the next enſuing year, where in other Writings he may be ſure to ſatisfie himſelf in the truth of the whole Proceedings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scotland</hi> knowing very well all the ſeveral tranſactions of <hi>England,</hi> and being well approved by them, take the ſame meaſures, and tread in the ſame ſteps, calling together the States of the Land, being the Nobility, Gentry, and other Degrees
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:59632:67"/> amongſt them, and being aſſembled, were likewiſe named a <hi>Convention,</hi> and afterwards a <hi>Parliament,</hi> who preſently addreſſed themſelves to our King, and humbly beg'd his Protection, and Proclaimed <hi>William</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> their <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Cuſtom, and after a little time came to <hi>London,</hi> tend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing their Crown by Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners to their Majeſties, which was accepted very graciouſly.</p>
            <p>Poor diſtreſſed <hi>Ireland</hi> however, the major (but in the genuine ſence) the better part thereof, would have willingly and chearfully followed the former Examples of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> but the Commands of the late King <hi>James,</hi> the crafty Projects of the <hi>French</hi> King, the fly Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Prieſts cloſely and hourly made—and applied to the Earl of <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> then Lord De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty, or at leaſt Governour of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> he alſo hoping by his not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to gain great Honour and
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:59632:67"/> Preferment; if not the whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try for his own proper uſe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit; but therein he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight eaſily perceive his errour, for <hi>Iewis</hi> that aſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing Monarch had deſign'd it long before to be annexed to his <hi>Flower de luces,</hi> but the poor <hi>Iriſh Harp</hi> would have cauſed but doleful Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick to the <hi>Hibernians;</hi> yet a melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious tune to the <hi>wooden ſhoo'd French,</hi> which would preſently have bin dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing in that Country; however the reaſons before mentioned, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de <hi>Tyrconnel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> ſo obſtinate, that with what Forces, and that little Courage he was poſſeſſed of, to defend and preſerve <hi>Ireland</hi> for his <hi>two M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſters:</hi> what the event was, ſome few years will tell you, however this light you ſhall have at preſent, that things pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved quite contrary, after ſeveral Conflicts and Battels, to his expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>But let us return into <hi>England,</hi> and there behold how many potent Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies the King had ſecured in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:59632:68"/> Priſons for the ſecurity of Their Majeſties Perſons, and the Kingdoms Welfare, Peace and Happineſs, <hi>viz. George Jefferies</hi> Baron of <hi>Wem,</hi> and Lord High Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Peterborough,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> the Lord <hi>Caſtlemain,</hi> the Lord <hi>Preſton,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Feverſham,</hi> the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Wright,</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron <hi>Jenner,</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Hale,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly Governour of <hi>Dover,</hi> and after Lieutenant of the Tower of <hi>London;</hi> and let <hi>Miles Prance,</hi> the Silver-Smith, a timely Diſcoverer, have the honour to be taken at <hi>Graveſend,</hi> with a falſe Paſs, and there committed to Priſon by the Secretary of War, when he intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to paſs the Seas. There were many more perſons of high and low rank taken into cuſtody, but by reaſon their Deliverances or Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als hereafter will make them more publick, I ſhall at preſent omit them all, except Dr. <hi>Obadiah Walker,</hi> the Proſelyte-maker at <hi>Oxford,</hi> who was
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:59632:68"/> ſent to the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> but not amongſt the Records to make ſearch for the place of Purgatory; but foretell his own fortune, either by calculating his Nativity, by the often Singing of his <hi>Ave Maria,</hi> or numbring his Beads at their appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Seaſons, whether by day or night<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but let <hi>Obadiah</hi> reſt, being accounted but one of the ſmall—</p>
            <p>There were alſo in this Juncture of time many perſons ſecured in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Counties of <hi>England,</hi> alway<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> having an eye and great care of the <hi>Red Letter-men,</hi> and of thoſe ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> headed-perſons that took places of Truſt and Commiſſions from the late King <hi>James,</hi> never regarding the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſt;</hi> the Prieſts like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe were apprehended as ſoon as diſcovered, yet not many, for know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their ſins to be of a dark colour, they would not abide the reckoning, but went off with the next Oars.</p>
            <p>Alſo about this time the King was vigilant over his Army that ſerved
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:59632:69"/> under the late King <hi>James,</hi> not ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring any of them at preſent to come for <hi>London,</hi> eſpecially in any great Parties, but ſent them into ſeveral Parts and Counties of <hi>England,</hi> by degrees modelling of them a new; firſt breaking the old Regiments both of Foot and Horſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and then formed them into new Bodies, ſo as to take away all ſuſpicion of their diſloyalty to their King, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps was unjuſtly caſt upon them; however by this honeſt Stratagem of War, all the known <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and thoſe that appeared diſaffected to the King and Government, were quite caſhiered; and then the King was ſo well ſatisfied with the remaining part, that they were ſent to <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall,</hi> and took their Guard-days in the ſame manner (as they had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly) part of that Army which came out of <hi>Holland,</hi> being of the Guards there, were either all, or in part, removed from that Station.</p>
            <pb n="129" facs="tcp:59632:69"/>
            <p> By this time the Reader may be pondering with himſelf, that there is an abſolute neceſſity for great Sums of Money, not only for defraying the charge of the Fleet that brought the King and his Army over into <hi>England,</hi> but likewiſe the vaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence and charges which our <hi>Engliſh Fleet</hi> and Army had brought upon the Nation; and theſe two Fleets and two Armies united, and all to be paid by one Maſter, would in a ſhort ſpace of time riſe and multiply to an incredible account.</p>
            <p>The Parliament taking this and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matters of the like nature, being of great concern, into their conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, after mature deliberation; Voted ſeveral Sums for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to be raiſed, <hi>viz.</hi> by additio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Exciſe of Ale, Beer, ſome ſmall Branch of the ſaid Revenue, being ready to drop down, was by a new A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t reunited, alſo a Land-Tax at 12 <hi>d. per</hi> Pound was Enacted by Parliament; the Cuſtoms and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:59632:70"/> other Duties belonging to the Crown, were by the ſaid Authority, confirmed and ſettled upon the King and Queen.</p>
            <p>The Affairs of the Kingdom now being in a hopeful way of Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as ſo ſmall a time had bin al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed for ſo great a change, and new modelling both of Perſons and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the King and Parliament in all matters very well concurring; the King was pleaſed amongſt other of his favours and elemency, to declare he would ſtand by, and defend the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> the Church of <hi>England</hi> as by <hi>Law eſtabliſhed,</hi> to his utmoſt power againſt all oppoſers whatſoever; and withal care ſhould be taken for the <hi>Non Con's,</hi> and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering Opinions, the Kings gracious pleaſure being thus publiſhed, made all his Subjects to be filled with joy, admiration and liberality to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, that the Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> of their own accord, proffered to lend the King what Money His Majeſty
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:59632:70"/> pleaſed, and almoſt in an inſtant, great and vaſt Sums of Money were brought into <hi>Guildhall,</hi> and that Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen thought himſelf the moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py which was the firſt leader, and brought the biggeſt Bags; for which at preſent, they were very willing to accept of the Kings word for their ſeveral ſecurities.</p>
            <p>The King by this time, being the latter end of <hi>March,</hi> having got in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to poſſeſſion ſome money, but that which equalized, or rather exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, the affections of his People; would have bin very happy toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by his peaceable Reign over his Subjects here in <hi>England,</hi> had not the Rebels in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> by the fair promiſes of Rewards and Preferments of the late King <hi>James</hi> and <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>14th</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> inſtigated, and hurried into Arms and bloody Wars againſt this King <hi>William;</hi> ſo that both <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> wanted his aſſiſtance, and being willing and ready, the King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:59632:71"/> to reduce them both to his obedience; but this Year being drawn to its period, and my figure to be out of date, becauſe I will not leap into another, but conclude my <hi>Eighty Eight,</hi> a Year full of Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Changes, yet in hopes it will be the introducer of <hi>England's Glory,</hi> and do verily believe, that future Generations will call it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, becauſe it reſtored <hi>Our Lives, Religion, Laws</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> and I deſire it may make us all truly thankful to him who was the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginner and finiſher of ſo great and good a work.</p>
            <p>By this time the Reader may give this account, that any man of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon being 58 years of Age in this Year of Jubilee 1688. may demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate and make it plainly appear to others of younger dates, that he has lived under Eight Governours and Governments, <hi>viz.</hi> In the Reign of King <hi>Car. I. Car. II. James II. Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> and is truly called
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:59632:71"/> Monarchy, then under the power and Tyranny of two perſons Regal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, in reſpect they were ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and had the power of Calling and Diſſolving Parliaments, making War and Peace, to condemn or ſave guilty Malefactors, Robbers and Rebels; and indeed <hi>Oliver</hi>'s power did much exceed that Authority which King <hi>Charles</hi> I. did take upon himſelf; yet this <hi>Oliver</hi> and his ſhort-Reign'd Succeſſor <hi>Richard,</hi> wanted the Crown, the Royal Title of a King, and were content to enjoy the Nomination of <hi>Protectors,</hi> with this addition upon the Great Seal of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> inſcribed, <hi>By Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He then was under the arbitrary will and diſpoſal of Parliaments, ends and pieces, formerly called the <hi>Rump Parliament,</hi> which in the laſt eight Years of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. were the ſole Lords and Rulers of <hi>England,</hi> raiſing War againſt their King, and likewiſe great Funds of Money, which was
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:59632:72"/> alſo raiſed by impoſition of the firſt Exciſe of Ale and Beer in <hi>England,</hi> and not only publick but every pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Houſe paid for all the Beer they brewed and conſumed; the Butchers in all places paid ſo much for a Cow, or Heifer, a Bull or Ox; ſo much a Calf, and alſo for Sheep; and ſix pence in the <hi>pound</hi> for all Woollen Cloth that was made and fold; and there was an impoſition upon Salt, and ſeveral other things in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. This <hi>Domus Communis,</hi> for brevities ſake <hi>Dom. Com.</hi> Voted down the Houſe of Lords, called the Upper Houſe, and Voted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Supream Power of the Nation, and this was performed by an intrinſick vertue, and an occult quality latent in their unknown Prerogatives, their Ordinances were more efficacious than our Acts are in theſe days.</p>
            <p>A blind Order from a beggerly Committee would fetch up a Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, put him into Priſon, take his
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:59632:72"/> Eſtate, and no Appeal to be made, but at <hi>Goldſmiths</hi> or <hi>Haberdaſhers-Hall,</hi> and there your compoſition was made upon ſuch hard terms, that the poor <hi>Cavalier</hi> was forced to ſell part of his Eſtate to ſave the reſt, and this puniſhment was inflicted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe that out of a Principle of Loyalty took up Arms in defence of their Prince and Country; let us paſs by the two <hi>Aping and counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit Kings, Oliver</hi> and his Son and Succeſſor <hi>Richard;</hi> only tell you, that the former would whip a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament out of the old Houſe in a moment, and becauſe he would have an able Parliament, he cauſed his own men, as well Troopers as Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, to be choſen Members there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>Let us not forget <hi>Barebon</hi>'s Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that zealous <hi>Leather-ſeller,</hi> who was taking care by bringing his Bills into the Houſe to extirpate the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of the <hi>Stewarts, Root</hi> and <hi>Branch.</hi> How he came by the name of <hi>Praiſe-God-Barebones,</hi>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:59632:73"/> is uncertain, but ſome of the Family has informed me, that the Conſtable and Watchmen of St. <hi>Martins Ludgate</hi> were his Godfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: however I am in hopes, that before he departed this life he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of his bad actions, and for the <hi>Act of Grace</hi> did truly <hi>Praiſe God,</hi> or elſe, <hi>Fare ill Barebones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then a <hi>Committee of Safety</hi> was appointed to regulate and govern this poor toſſed Commonweal, much diſtempered, and ſo much out of Order, that this new-formed Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioned Company knew not how to behave themſelves in their New Corporation, only made ſome ſmall offers of Reformation, and of ſetling a firm peace to their ſimple and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Admirers; put out their new lights, ſeeing they could proceed no farther, every man diſſolved his own individual body, and retreated into the old <hi>Dom. Com.</hi> and there ſtayed till General <hi>Monk</hi> came out of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> for <hi>London,</hi> and played a new
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:59632:73"/> Game with them, and made the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful King, <hi>Charta Dominatrix,</hi> to rule over all the reſt. Theſe laſt four Milcellanies <hi>Hotchpotch Gallimawf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Governments,</hi> at leaſt ſo called, muſt be denominated <hi>Democracy,</hi> being a fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ious and confuſed Government of the uncertain and diſſatisfied People of <hi>England,</hi> this laſt Page had been omitted, not falling under my figure, but it gave clear demonſtrations how to bring in 48 and 58. Their dark actions being diſcovered in theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervals, I judged they might ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in this place be interpoſed. And now Reader, having brought thee, according to my promiſe, under the figure of 8 to the year 1688, I leave thee there, and bid thee Meditate on what was acted therein, and heartily<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wiſh that the remembrance of that 88, may admit no</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="138" facs="tcp:59632:74"/>
            <head>AN APPENDIX.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>REginald Pole,</hi> Born at <hi>Stover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Caſtle</hi> in <hi>Staffordſhire,</hi> was ſecond Son to Sir <hi>Richard,</hi> Knight of the Garter, and nearly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to King <hi>Henry</hi> 7. His Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Margaret</hi> Counteſs of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> was Niece to King <hi>Edward</hi> 4. and Daughter to <hi>George</hi> Duke of <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence;</hi> He was bred in <hi>Corpus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxford,</hi> preferred afterwards Dean of <hi>Exeter, Henry</hi> the <hi>8th.</hi> allowing him a Penſion, ſent him beyond the Seas. He ſtudied at <hi>Padua,</hi> converſed much with the Patricians of <hi>Venice,</hi> and in ſine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a perfect <hi>Italian,</hi> and could not be prevailed upon by the King, or his friends, to return to <hi>England,</hi> whereupon his Penſion was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn, living afterwards in a <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:59632:74"/> Monaſtery. He attained great Credit for his Eloquence, Learning and good Life. It was not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was made <hi>Deacon Cardinal,</hi> by the Title of <hi>St. Mary in Coſme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din,</hi> by Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the 3d, who ſent him Ambaſſador to the Emperor and <hi>French</hi> King, to incite them to War againſt K. <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. He afterwards retired to <hi>Viterbo</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> where his Houſe was the Sanctuary of the <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans,</hi> where he himſelf became a <hi>racking,</hi> but no <hi>through-paced Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant,</hi> inſomuch that being appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one of the three Preſidents of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> he endeavoured to have <hi>Juſtification</hi> determined by <hi>Faith alone;</hi> during his living at <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbo,</hi> he was taxed for getting a <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard,</hi> which <hi>Paſquil</hi> publiſhed in Verſes affixed to his Pillar, that Blade being made of all tongue and teeth, would not ſtick to tell where the Pope trod his holy Sandals awry. Yet he had ſome Relation to the Beaſt in the <hi>Apocalypſe,</hi> in that under
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:59632:75"/> the name of <hi>Paſquil,</hi> there has been a <hi>Succeſſive Corporation of Satyriſts.</hi> After the death of <hi>Paul</hi> 3. <hi>Pole</hi> was at Midnight in the Conclave choſen to ſucceed him, the refuſal whereof un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the notion of <hi>a Deed of Darkneſs,</hi> was by the <hi>Italians</hi> lookt upon as a piece of dulneſs in our Cardinal: next day expecting a re-election, he ſaw <hi>Julius</hi> the 3<hi>d.</hi> his profeſſed Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my choſen in his place, yet after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, he became <hi>alterius Orbis Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa,</hi> when made Archbiſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi> by Queen <hi>Mary.</hi> He was a perſon free from Paſſion. His youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Books are full of the flowers of Rhetorick, whilſt thoſe of his old age are dry and dull. He died a few hours after Queen <hi>Mary, Novemb.</hi> 17. 1558. at <hi>Lambeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>John Cavendiſh</hi> Knight, born at <hi>Cavendiſh</hi> in <hi>Suffolk</hi> (where his name continued untill the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> 8.) was made Lord Chief Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the <hi>Kings-Bench, anno.</hi> 46 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. he died a violent death, <hi>an.</hi>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:59632:75"/> 5 <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. on this occaſion, <hi>J. Raw,</hi> Prieſt contemporary with <hi>J. Straw</hi> and <hi>Wat. Tyler,</hi> advanced <hi>Robert Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broom</hi> a Clown to be King of the Commons in this County, having 50000 Followers, theſe for eight days together, in ſavage ſport, cauſed the Heads of Great Perſons to be cut off, and ſet on Poles to kiſs and whiſper in one anothers ears; Chief Juſtice <hi>Cavendiſh</hi> chanced to be then in the Country, to whom they bare a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Pique, for his honeſty and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; beſides, they had heard that <hi>John Cavendiſh,</hi> his Kinſman, had kill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Idol <hi>Wat. Tyler</hi> in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> whereupon they drag'd the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Judge, with Sir <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge, Prior of Bury,</hi> to the Market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place, and there beheaded them, whoſe innocent bloud remained not long unrevenged by <hi>Spencer</hi> the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Biſhop of <hi>Norwich,</hi> by whom this Raſcal Rabble of Rebels was rooted and ruined.</p>
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:59632:76"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Leonard Maw</hi> was born at <hi>Rendle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham</hi> in <hi>Suffolk</hi> (antiently the Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Kings of <hi>E. Angles,</hi> where King <hi>Redwald</hi> kept at the ſame time a Communion-Table and Altars for Idols) was Maſter of <hi>Peter-Houſe,</hi> then of <hi>Trinity Colledge</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and in five years diſengaged that Foundation from a great Debt. He was Chaplain to King <hi>Charles</hi> whilſt he was Prince, and waited on him in <hi>Spain,</hi> by whom he was made Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells,</hi> a good Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, grave Preacher, mild man, and gentile in his deportment. He died in 1638. and left ſome of his Eſtate to Mr. <hi>Simon Maw</hi> of <hi>Epworth</hi> in <hi>Lincolnſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Fulk Grevil,</hi> Kt. Son to Sir <hi>Fulk</hi> Senior of <hi>Beckam-Court Warw.</hi> was bred in <hi>Cambridge.</hi> He came to Court, backt with a fair Eſtate in the Reign of Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> He was a good Scholar, and a great friend to learned Men. Biſhop <hi>Overall</hi> ow'd his Preferment chiefly to him, and
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:59632:76"/> Mr. <hi>Camden</hi> taſted largely of his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality. His Studies were moſt in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etry and Hiſtory, as his Works do witneſs. King <hi>James</hi> created him Baron <hi>Brook</hi> of <hi>Beauchamp Court,</hi> as deſcended from the ſole Daughter and Heir of <hi>Edward Willoughby,</hi> the late Lord <hi>Brook.</hi> He was murdered 1608. by a diſcontented Servant, who conceived himſelf not ſoon or well enough rewarded, firſt wounded his Maſter mortally, and afterwards diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched himſelf. He lieth buried in <hi>Warwick</hi> Church, under a fair Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whereon he is ſtiled, Servant to Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Counſellor to King <hi>James,</hi> and Friend to Sir <hi>Phillip Sidney,</hi> dying unmarried, his Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deſcended on his Kinſman, <hi>Robert Grevil,</hi> Lord <hi>Brook,</hi> Father to the Right Honourable <hi>Robert</hi> Lord <hi>Brook.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Morton</hi> was Son to a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Mercer</hi> (reputed the firſt in <hi>York)</hi> and allied to Cardinal <hi>Morton</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> He was
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:59632:77"/> bred in York-School (with that Arch-Traitor <hi>Guy Faux)</hi> and afterwards in St. <hi>Johns</hi> College in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and (for his merit) was choſen Fellow thereof; before eight Competitors, commencing <hi>D. D.</hi> He made his <hi>Poſition</hi> on his ſecond Queſtion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the expectation of Dr. <hi>Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> replying upon him with ſome Paſſion, <hi>commoviſti mihi ſtomachum,</hi> to whom <hi>Morton</hi> replied, <hi>Gratulor tibi, Reverende Profeſſor, de bono tuo ſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho, coenabis mecum hac nocte.</hi> He was ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively preferred Dean of <hi>Glouceſter, Wincheſter,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter, Coven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> and <hi>Lichfield,</hi> and <hi>Durham.</hi> The Foundation which he laid of foreign Correſpondency with eminent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of different Perſwaſions, when he attended as Chaplain to the Lord <hi>Evers</hi> (ſent by King <hi>James</hi> Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor to the King of <hi>Denmark, &amp;c.)</hi> he built upon to the day of his Death. In the late <hi>Long Parliament,</hi> the diſpleaſure of the Houſe of Gom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons fell heavy upon him, partly for
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:59632:77"/> ſubſcribing the Biſhops Proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for their Votes in Parliament, partly, for refuſing to reſign the Seal of his Biſhoprick, and baptizing a Daughter of <hi>John</hi> Earl of <hi>Rutland</hi> with the <hi>Sign of the Croſs;</hi> two faults which compounded together in the judgment of wiſe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men, amounted to an high in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence; yet the Parliament allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him 800 <hi>l.</hi> a year (a proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on above his brethren) for his Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, but the Trumpet of their Charity gave an uncertain ſound, not aſſigning by whom, or whence this ſum ſhould be paid. Indeed the <hi>Severe Votes of Parliament</hi> ever took full effect, according to his obſervation who did Anagram it, <hi>Voted Outed.</hi> But their merciful Votes found not ſo free performance, How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever this good Biſhop got 1000 <hi>l.</hi> out of <hi>Goldſmiths-Hall,</hi> which afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him ſupport in his old Age. He wrote againſt <hi>Faction,</hi> in defence of three innocent <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> and
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:59632:78"/> againſt <hi>Superſtition</hi> in his Treatiſe called the <hi>Grand Impoſtor.</hi> Many of the Nobility deſervedly honoured him, but none more than <hi>John</hi> Earl of <hi>Rutland,</hi> to whoſe Kinſman, <hi>Roger</hi> Earl of <hi>Rutland,</hi> he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly been Chaplain. Sir <hi>George Savil</hi> civilly paid him his purchaſed annuity of 200 <hi>l.</hi> He died at <hi>Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Manduit</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> the Houſe of Sir <hi>Henry Yelverton,</hi> aged near 98.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>George Paling</hi> born at <hi>Wrenbury</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> was bred a Merchant in <hi>London,</hi> Free of the Company of <hi>Girdlers.</hi> We may call his Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, <hi>The golden Girdle of Charity,</hi> for with our Saviour, <hi>He went about doing good.</hi> To <hi>Wrenbury</hi> he gave 200<hi>l.</hi> to purchaſe Lands for the relief of the Poor. For building of an Alms-Houſe in and about <hi>London</hi> 900 <hi>l.</hi> To St. <hi>Johns</hi> College in <hi>Cambridge</hi> 300 <hi>l.</hi> To the Hoſpital of St. <hi>Thomas</hi> in <hi>Southwark</hi> 50 <hi>l.</hi> To the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers at St. <hi>Pauls Croſs</hi> 200 <hi>pounds.</hi> To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:59632:78"/> a <hi>Chime</hi> in Bow-Church 100 <hi>pounds.</hi> To ſix Priſons in and about <hi>London</hi> 60 <hi>pounds.</hi> To <hi>Braſen-Noſe</hi> College in <hi>Oxford,</hi> two Scholarſhips, to each yearly 4 <hi>pounds.</hi> To the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of St <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> two Scholarſhips of the ſame value. To <hi>Chriſts-Church-Hoſpital</hi> 300 <hi>l.</hi> To the Church and Poor of <hi>Wrenbury,</hi> to buy them Gowns 70 <hi>pounds.</hi> He di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 1608.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>James Pilkington D. D.</hi> of an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Family, before the Conqueſt, (when the chief of them then ſought for) diſguiſed himſelf a <hi>Threſher,</hi> has for his Motto, <hi>Now thus, now thus,</hi> in Alluſion to the <hi>Head</hi> of his Flail, or to himſelf embracing the ſafeſt condition for the preſent. He was bred in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and fled <hi>an.</hi> 1. of <hi>Mariae</hi> into <hi>Germany,</hi> where he wrote a Comment on <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> and the Epiſtles of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> after his return he was made Biſhop of <hi>Durham</hi> 1558, and nine years after the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern</hi> Rebels came to <hi>Durham,</hi> and
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:59632:79"/> tore the <hi>Engliſh Liturgy,</hi> the Biſhop had fared no better if they had found him; when the Rebellion was ſuppreſs'd, the Biſhop commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced a Suit againſt Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> for the Lands and Goods of the Rebels attainted in the Biſhoprick, as due to him: but the Parliament interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing on ſpecial conſideration, <hi>pro hoc tempore,</hi> adjudg'd them to the Queen, and after eight years of the Rebellion he died in peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Eaſday,</hi> of moſt honourable Extraction, bred in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> was Dean of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> He was the firſt Clergy-man who carried Tidings of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Crown to King <hi>James.</hi> He reduced the Court of <hi>Trinity</hi> Colledge to a ſpacious and beautiful Quadrangle, and added a ſtately new Court at his own expence of above three hundred pounds. He di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 1618.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard Rich</hi> Knight, well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended, was Sollicitor to <hi>Henry</hi> 8. upon his Depoſition chiefly, Sir <hi>Tho.</hi>
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:59632:79"/> 
               <hi>More</hi> was beheaded. Under <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel</hi> he was a leſſer Hammer to knock down Abbies, ſome of which ſtuck (juſtly) to his fingers. By <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. He was made Lord Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> being an oppoſer of <hi>D. Dudley,</hi> he reſigned his Office by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, having got a fair Eſtate at <hi>Lees</hi> Abby in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> whereof he was Baron. He died in 1558. being direct Anceſtor to the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Charles Rich,</hi> now Earl of <hi>Warwick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard Mulcarter,</hi> of ancient Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, was born in <hi>Weſtmorland,</hi> and bred in <hi>Kings</hi> Gollege in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> afterwards in <hi>Oxford.</hi> He was choſen the firſt Maſter of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant-Taylors</hi> School in <hi>London,</hi> where his Scholars proſited ſo well, that the <hi>Merchant Taylors</hi> intended to ſix him, as his Desk, to their School, till Death ſhould remove him: this he perceived, and therefore gave for his Motto, <hi>fidelis ſervus, perpetuus aſinus;</hi> but after twenty five years,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:59632:80"/> he was made Maſter of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s School. Such was his Diſcipline, that the Indulgence of Parents, rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed than mitigated his ſeverity on their offending Children. He was <hi>plagioſus Orbilius,</hi> and (which qualified the matter) <hi>unpartial:</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the many excellent Scholars which he bred, Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> was moſt remarkable: At laſt, quitting the place, he became Parſon of <hi>Standford-Rivers,</hi> and died very a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, <hi>Anno</hi> 1578.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Wilford,</hi> born nigh <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> was a valiant and ſucceſsful Seaman: After the <hi>French</hi> had by a ſuddain Invaſion burnt ſeveral hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of Houſes in <hi>Plimouth,</hi> on that ſide of the Town called ſince <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain-ſide,</hi> he took 40 Ships on the Coaſts of the <hi>Britains,</hi> and burnt as many at <hi>Penarch,</hi> repaying the Monſieurs in their own Coin. He died in 1508.</p>
            <pb n="151" facs="tcp:59632:80"/>
            <p> This brave exploit was done in the Reign of <hi>Edw.</hi> IV.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>John Popham,</hi> of moſt ancient Deſcent, was born at <hi>Huntworth</hi> in <hi>Somerſetſhire;</hi> when a Youth, he was ſtout, and well skill'd at Sword and Buckler, and wild enough in his Recreations: Afterwards he applied himſelf to a more profitable <hi>Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing,</hi> the Study of the Common-Laws, wherein he became Eminent. He was preferred the Queen's At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney, and afterwards Lord Chief Juſtice of <hi>England.</hi> He depoſed upon his Oath, in open Court, at the Tryal of the Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> 1600. That he had been <hi>violently detained</hi> at the Earl's Houſe, by his Military Men there aſſembled, which ſome conceived <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>antamount to an Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment. Note the rarity of the precedent. He cut aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nder the knot of Northern Robbers, and others, with the Sword of Juſtice: He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented effectually to King <hi>James,</hi>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:59632:81"/> the inconvenience of frequent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons. He uſed <hi>exemplary Severity</hi> againſt Malefactors (ſhunning the dangerous Rock of <hi>cruel Mercy,)</hi> whereby the Lives of many Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands were preſerved. He died <hi>an.</hi> 1608.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omas James,</hi> born in the <hi>Iſle of Wight,</hi> D. D. and Keeper of the Library of <hi>Oxford,</hi> was a Member of the Convocation held with the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>Oxford,</hi> I. <hi>Car.</hi> where he made a <hi>motion,</hi> that ſome might be Commiſſioned to peruſe the <hi>Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript Fathers,</hi> in all <hi>Engliſh Libraries,</hi> for detecting Popiſh Editions. He was Sub-Dean of <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lls,</hi> and died 1628.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Will. Mounſon,</hi> Kt. of an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ient Family in <hi>Lincolnſh.</hi> was made Vice-Admiral in <hi>an. primo Jac.</hi> (S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r <hi>Richard Leveſon</hi> Admiral,) by whoſe diligence and valour, Trading was killed on the Coaſts of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and a Caract of 1600 Tun taken, which had in her 300 Spaniſh Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:59632:81"/> and amounted to the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of 1000000 Crowns of <hi>Portugal</hi> account; though the Marqueſs <hi>de Sancta Cruce</hi> lay hard by with 13 Ships, and all were ſecured under the Command of a ſtrong Caſtle; in the <hi>Diſpute,</hi> the <hi>Syllogiſms</hi> of <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Sword,</hi> which were uſed by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> (tho' the <hi>Premiſes</hi> were oppoſed with the beſt <hi>Spaniſh Logic,)</hi> were anſwered by the Opponent, with a fair <hi>conceſſion.</hi> In the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the Goods gotten in the Caract might be valued, but the Good gained thereby, was ineſtimable; for henceforward the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> beheld the <hi>Engliſh</hi> with admiration, and quitted their Thoughts of Invaſion. This worthy Knight died, according to the beſt computation, in 1608. The Family ſtill Flouriſheth with a very large and plentiful Eſtate of 6000 <hi>l. per Annum,</hi> at <hi>Burton,</hi> near, (or as ſome call it under) <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:59632:82"/>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:59632:82"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Catalogue of Books lately Printed for, and Sold by</hi> John Weld, <hi>at the</hi> Crown <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Two</hi> Temple-Gates <hi>in</hi> Fleet-ſtreet.</head>
            <p n="1">1. AN Hiſtorical Account of making the Penal Laws by the Papiſts againſt the Proteſtants, and by the Proteſtants againſt the Papiſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The true <hi>Ground</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> of making the ſaid <hi>Laws</hi> being very neceſſary to be known by all Gentlemen and Practitioners of the Law. Fol. By <hi>Samuel Blackerby,</hi> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſter of <hi>Grays-Inn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Sacrifice; a Tragedy. Written by the Honourable Sir <hi>Francis Fane,</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bath.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:59632:83"/> In Quarto. The Second Edition En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Mr. <hi>Henry Hurſt</hi>'s Funeral Sermon. Preached and Publiſhed at the earneſt Deſire of his Relatives and People. By <hi>Richard Adams,</hi> M. A. ſometimes Fellow of <hi>Brafen-Noſe</hi> College in <hi>Oxon.</hi> Quarto</p>
            <p n="4">4. A New Diſcovery of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Methods of <hi>France,</hi> to Fruſtrate the Glorious Deſigns of the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Princes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Wherein is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſome ſecret Paſſages, (never before known to the World,) how the late King <hi>James</hi> was only made a <hi>French</hi> Tool, during his ſhort Reign, to enſlave theſe Three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms to the unſupportable Tyranny of <hi>France.</hi> Quarto.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Lives of Famous and Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Men, who lived before our Bleſſed Saviours Nativity: Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into <hi>Engliſh</hi> by ſeveral ingenious
<pb facs="tcp:59632:83"/> Gentlemen in the Univerſity of <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> for the benefit of ſuch as do not underſtand the Original Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. Octavo.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The Life of God in the Soul of Man: Or, The Nature and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the Chriſtian Religion: with the Methods of attaining the <hi>Happineſs</hi> it propoſes: Alſo an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the beginnings and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of a Spiritual Life: With a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face. By Right the Reverend Father in God, <hi>Gilbert</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Sarum.</hi> The Second Edition, Corrected, to which is added a <hi>Table.</hi> Octavo.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>England</hi>'s Alarm: Or, The <hi>French</hi> King's Cruelties expoſed. Containing a true account of what Uſage theſe Three Nations may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, if ever they are ſo unhappy as to become a Prey to that moſt <hi>Cruel</hi> and <hi>Bloody Tyrant.</hi> Octavo.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb facs="tcp:59632:84"/> 8. A Diſcourſe of Wit; wherein is ſhown what is meant by it; the Cauſes, Variety, Original, Progreſs, and Signs of it; with a Character of a great Wit, and of one that is only a pretender thereto: Alſo the Ingenious Art of Writing and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlating well; with a pleaſant Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, whether Women can be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Witty, or no. The Objections alleg'd that they cannot be Witty anſwered, and the contrary plainly proved, by their Sagacity in mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Intriegues, whether good or bad; with a true Story of a Lady's Dexterity to be rid of two Husbands at once, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Twelves.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Dr. <hi>A. Horneck</hi>'s Practical Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the great Neceſſity and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſpenſible Obligation, which lies upon every Chriſtian, to apply him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf betimes to the Serious Practice of Religion. Twelves.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59632:84"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
